<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's jests refin'd and improv'd being a choice collection of the merriest jests, smartest repartee's, wittiest sayings, and most notable bulls, yet extant with many new ones, never before printed. To which are added, XI[V]. ingenious characters drawn to the life. The whole work compil'd with great care and exactness: and may serve as the witty-man's companion, the busy-man's diversion, and the melancholy-man's physick and recreation. The second edition with additions. Calculated for the innocent spending of the winter evenings, by H.C.</title>
            <author>Crouch, Humphrey, fl. 1635-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7277A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231051</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896649</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135151</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135151)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2427:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's jests refin'd and improv'd being a choice collection of the merriest jests, smartest repartee's, wittiest sayings, and most notable bulls, yet extant with many new ones, never before printed. To which are added, XI[V]. ingenious characters drawn to the life. The whole work compil'd with great care and exactness: and may serve as the witty-man's companion, the busy-man's diversion, and the melancholy-man's physick and recreation. The second edition with additions. Calculated for the innocent spending of the winter evenings, by H.C.</title>
                  <author>Crouch, Humphrey, fl. 1635-1671.</author>
                  <author>Drapentier, Jan, fl. 1674-1713, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 173, [10] p., [1] leaf of plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Harris, at the Harrow against the Church in the Poultrey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>H.C. = Humphrey Crowley.</note>
                  <note>Frontis. plate signed at foot "I. Drapentier", i.e. Jan Drapentier.</note>
                  <note>With 5 final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1641-1700 reel 2427 lacks final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>UMI reel guide incorrectly lists this as at postion 2 on reel 2427.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English wit and humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135151:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portraits of eight men</figDesc>
                  <p>ENGLAND'S JESTS REFIN'D AND IMPROV'D</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Scoggin.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Will. Soomers.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Archee</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>T. K.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Amner.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Capt. Hicks.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Poor. Robin.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Head.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Spectatum admiſsi Riſum teneatis Amici <bibl>Hora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </bibl>
                     </hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London Printted for John Harris aty<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Harrow iny<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <byline>I. Drapentier</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135151:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ENGLAND</hi>'s JESTS <hi rend="blackletterType">Refin'd and Improv'd</hi> Being a Choice COLLECTION OF THE Merrieſt Jeſts, Smarteſt Repar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee's, Wittieſt Sayings, and moſt Notable Bulls, yet Extant <hi rend="blackletterType">With many New Ones, never before Printed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TO WHICH ARE ADDED, XI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ingenious CHARACTERS</hi> 
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Drawn to the Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole WORK compil'd with great Care and Exactneſs: And may ſerve as the Witty-Man's COMPANION, the Buſy-Man's DIVERSION, and the Melancholy-Man's PHYSICK and RECREATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition with Additions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Calculated for the Innocent ſpending of the Winter Evenings, By <hi>H. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Semel in Anno Ridet Apollo.</l> 
               <bibl>Horat.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Harris,</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> againſt the Church in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1687.</p>
            <p>Price Bound One Shilling.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:135151:2"/>
            <p>LICENS'd, And Entred According to Order.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:135151:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I know and own <hi>Plain-Dealing</hi> to be a Jewel, ſo I were much to blame if I did not uſe it with You: Therefore as a taſte thereof, there were Two Reaſons that chiefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd me to compile this ſmall Piece, and which I propos'd to my ſelf as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he End thereof, <hi>viz. Your Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure,</hi> and <hi>my own Profit.</hi> For let Men pretend what they will for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Scribling, as the Information, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſtruction, or Obligation of their Friends and Countreymen, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wenty other Reaſons given for it; muſt beg their Pardons if I can't
<pb facs="tcp:135151:3"/> ſcrew up my Faith to believe 'em: For 'tis too plain that Intereſt ſways the World, and that all ſorts and degrees of Men, even from the <hi>Courtier</hi> to the <hi>Cobler,</hi> are its Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries. You will not then admire if I propos'd it to my ſelf; nor do I think that I ſtood in need of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to convince you of it: But <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> calling for one, a Book being without it (as our Modern Wits ſay) Like a Houſe without a Porch, or a Play without a Prologue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Tho I must confeſs I am no great admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of Prefaces, looking upon 'em, I mean the Generality of 'em, (for there are ſome that are Conciſe, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and Inſtructive) to be for the most part Impertinent, Superfluous and little to the purpoſe; ſtuft wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Flattery and Ostentation, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny times exceſſive long and tedious like too much Ceremony before good Feaſt; which by its long d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taining a man, palls his Appetit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Notwithſtanding which, I was wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:135151:3"/> to give you ſome ſhort accoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of this Book; which you will find to be a choice Collection of the Merrieſt Jeſts, &amp;c. (as you may ſee in the Title Page, to which I refer you) Extracted from the ſeveral Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors that have written on thoſe Subjects; Wherein their Gold is ſeparated from their Droſs, their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npolite Ones are Refin'd, their long and tedious Ones Retrench'd, their Old Ones render'd Modern, and thoſe unworthy an Ingenious Man's Reading, wholy left out; The Compoſure thereof, having cost me no ſmall Care and Pains, as you may judge; that not only the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over, but Critical Examination of the ſeveral Books written (as aforeſaid) on thoſe Subjects, muſt needs amount to. But perhaps ſome carping <hi>Zoilus,</hi> or ſevere <hi>Cato,</hi> will either blame the Compoſure of theſe Jests, or utterly deny the uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of any. As to the first, I leave it to your Cander to judge of
<pb facs="tcp:135151:4"/> it, knowing that if you come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light your Self with Ingenious Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and not to Carp, you may find ſome in this <hi>Collection</hi> of the Choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt, that may anſwer your Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation: But if there ſtill remain any that ought to be Expung'd, paſs 'em by; and let the Merits of the Majority atone for their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. To the latter Objection againſt all manner of Jests, I think <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> will be a ſufficient Apollogy, eſpecially ſince they do not interfere with Religion, or good Manners. But I leave the whole to your peruſal; Hoping that as I have done what lay in my Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to contribute to your Pleaſure and Delight, ſo you will do your part, and ſhow your kind acceptance thereof in buying it, eſpecially when you may have it at ſo Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable a Rate as One Shilling.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell,</salute> 
               <signed>H. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135151:4"/>
            <head>ENGLAND'S <hi>JESTS</hi> Refin'd and Improv'd.</head>
            <div type="anecdotes">
               <p>
                  <label>1.</label> 
                  <hi>APelles</hi> the Famous Painter, having drawn the Picture of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great on Horſeback, and preſented it to him, he gave it not that Praiſe that ſo Exquiſite a Piece deſerved; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Apelles</hi> deſir'd a Living Horſe might be brought, who ſeeing the Picture, fell to Pawing and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, taking it to be a real Rival; Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which <hi>Apelles</hi> ingeniouſly told that Great Emperour, <hi>That his Horſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood Painting better then He.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:135151:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label>2.</label> An Ignorant Countrey-man coming to Town, went to <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> to a Gentleman to whom he was dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; who out of civility to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey man, ſhew'd him what was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable thereabouts, as the <hi>Piazza's,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſeveral Perſons of Qualities ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Houſes: At length he came to the Church, and the Countrey-man poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, asked the Gentleman whoſe Houſe that was? He told him it was <hi>the Lord of Hoſts:</hi> The Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man having never heard of ſuch a Lord before, reply'd, <hi>It was ſome Scotch Lord, he'd warrant him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>3.</label> A Gentleman of <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> laſt laſt Winter, deſir'd another of the ſame <hi>Inn</hi> to lend him <hi>Bakers</hi> Chronicle for an hour or two: He ſent him word, That he could not ſpare it out of his Chamber, but if he pleas'd to come thither, he might uſe it all day there. Not long after, the other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman deſir'd him to lend him his Bellows: he ſent him word, <hi>He could not ſpare them out of his Chamber but if he pleas'd to come thither he might uſe them all day long there.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135151:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label>4.</label> A Mayor of a certain Corporation dining with the Aldermen his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; after Dinner, to ſhew his Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, began his Majeſties health on one Knee, and preſented it to one of the Aldermen, whom he imagin'd to be no great Admirer of Health-Drinking; The Alderman took the Glaſs, and pledg'd him on both Knees; which the reſt of his Brethren obſerving, the Loyal Mayor was not a little concern'd to be out-done (as he thought) by the Alderman, and ask'd him why he did it not as he had begun it, on one Knee? <hi>Why truly</hi> (ſays the Alderman) <hi>one Knee was in Honour of the King, and the other to ask God Forgiveneſs for ſo doing:</hi> What, (ſays the Mayor) for doing the King Honour? <hi>No</hi> (ſays he) <hi>not for that, but becauſe I pledg'd a Health on that which I ought to pray on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>5.</label> A <hi>Spaniard</hi> and a <hi>Frenchman</hi> meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> after the uſual Complements paſs'd between them, fell to diſputing about Religion; <hi>Why</hi> (quoth the <hi>Spaniard) will you contend with us about Religion? There are more Saints in</hi> Spain <hi>then, I have Hairs on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135151:6"/> my Beard: And there are more in</hi> France (ſaid the <hi>Frenchman) then I have Hairs on my Head and Beard too.</hi> Then ſaid the <hi>Spaniard, let the conteſt be thus decided, I will pull a Hair off your Beard, for every Saint I name; and you ſhall pluck one off mine, for every Saint you name:</hi> So the <hi>Frenchman</hi> began, and pull'd one off the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard's</hi> Beard, crying St. <hi>Dennis;</hi> then the <hi>Spaniard</hi> doing the like, ſaid St. <hi>Ignace:</hi> The <hi>Frenchman</hi> pulling ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, cry'd St. <hi>Martin;</hi> the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> St. <hi>Xavier;</hi> the <hi>Frenchman,</hi> St. <hi>Lovis;</hi> the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> St. <hi>Tereſe;</hi> the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> St. <hi>Clotilde;</hi> the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> St. <hi>Iſidore;</hi> the <hi>Frenchman,</hi> St. <hi>Bun;</hi> the <hi>Spaniard</hi> pulling two at once, cry'd, St. <hi>Coſme</hi> and St. <hi>Phillip;</hi> the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> reſolving to be reveng'd, pluck'd off a whole Muſtache, ſaying, <hi>The Eleven Thouſand Virgins:</hi> Upon this, the Conteſt ended; the <hi>Spaniard</hi> not being able to endure or parallel ſo great a number.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>6.</label> A Countrey-fellow thatching a Houſe, had an arch Boy to ſerve him with Straw; now there comes by a great Hog, and turns up his Head,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135151:6"/> as if he were liſtening; ſays the Thatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then to the Boy, <hi>What does that Hog think now?</hi> O (ſays the witty Rogue) <hi>I'll warrant you he's hatching of Miſchief:</hi> And while he was buſie at his work on the Ladder, the Boy hunted the Hog juſt towards it, and juſtling againſt it, down came the Ladder, and Man and all: <hi>Pox on you,</hi> ſays this Blockhead to the Hog, <hi>'tis true as the honeſt Boy ſaid, you were hatching of Miſchief indeed; for I think my Shoulder's out; and if ever I thatch for any Body hereafter, I'll make my Bargain with them, that they ſhall all tye up their Hogs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>7.</label> Two young Scholars travelling from <hi>Roan</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> met a Countrey fellow riding upon an Aſs, which bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſuch a manner, as if he had been over-joy'd to be in ſuch learned Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: Theſe Students thinking to put a trick on the Fellow, ſaid, <hi>Friend, why do you let your Brother cry ſo? Can't you find out ſome way to ſtill and quiet him?</hi> The Fellow, who was none of the dulleſt of the Pariſh that he dwelt in, anſwered, <hi>My Aſs, Sirs, is ſoextreamly pleas'd to meet with his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135151:7"/> Relations and Old Acquaintance, that he cou'd do no leſs than ſing a Song of mirth and merry glee, in teſtimony of your hearty Welcom to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>8.</label> One told a Gentleman, That he wou'd willingly marry, but he wou'd have a Wife that is perfectly good: To whom the Gentleman reply'd, <hi>That if none but ſuch a one wou'd ſerve his turn, he muſt beſpeak her, for there was no ſuch ready made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>9.</label> Two young Students were in a deep diſpute about the Man in the Moon, whether he was a Gentleman or a Citizen; and after a great many <hi>Pro</hi>'s and <hi>Con</hi>'s between them, one of them very wittily ſolv'd it thus: <hi>When the Moon was at Full, then there was a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in her; but when ſhe appear'd with two Horns, then he might ſwear there was a Cit in her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>10.</label> Three Souldiers talking together, were over-heard by a Courtier to ſay thus: One ſaid, <hi>Had he a Thouſand Pounds, he ſhould be happier then the King</hi> the other ſaid, <hi>Were he a Captain under the King, he ſhould be happier then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135151:7"/> he;</hi> the third ſaid, <hi>That had he one Nights Lodging with the Queen, he ſhould be the happieſt man in the World.</hi> The Courtier related this to the King, and his Majeſty (for Divertiſement) ſent for the three Souldiers the next day before him; and commanded them to tell him what they ſaid the night before at ſuch a time. The firſt, fearing the Kings Diſpleaſure, ſaid, That he had indeed raſhly ſaid, <hi>That if he had a thouſand Pounds, he ſhould be as happy as the King;</hi> ſo the King commanded a Thouſand Pounds ſhould be given him: The Second begg'd his Majeſties Pardon for his bold ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That had he a Captains Command under him, he ſhould be as happy as he;</hi> then the King confer'd that honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Office upon him. Then the third fell upon his Knees, imploring his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Pardon, for that he had ſaid, <hi>That if he lay one Night with the Queen, he ſhould be the happieſt man in the World. Well,</hi> ſaid the King, <hi>that is not in my Power to grant; but if you can get her conſent, you ſhall have mine:</hi> So he brought him before his Queen, and told his Petition; but the Queen, to ſhew that our deſires ought to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135151:8"/> on ſuitable Objects, caus'd him to be ſoundly whipt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>11.</label> A witty young Fellow was try'd for his Life, ſince his Majeſties Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and being caſt, they told him he muſt be hang'd: But he pleaded in his own defence a long time; at laſt deſir'd the Judge, <hi>That if he muſt be hang'd, he might be hang'd after the new way that</hi> Oliver <hi>was, three or four years after he was dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>12.</label> One that was advis'd to marry a Widow, reply'd, That they were too Politick a Generation for him; which he prov'd by Similies: <hi>Many Voyages</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>make an expert Seaman, many Offices, a Crafty Knave; and many Marriages, a Cunning Falſe Widow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>13.</label> A Juſtice of Peace overtaking a Parſon upon the Road, between <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>Bow,</hi> told his Company that he would put a Trick upon him; and ſo coming up to him, ſaid, <hi>Sir, You don't follow your Maſters Rule, for he was content with an Aſs, but you have a very fine Horſe:</hi> The Parſon reply'd,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135151:8"/> The Reaſon was, <hi>becauſe the King had made ſo many Aſſes Juſtices, that a Clergy-man could not get one to Ride on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>14.</label> A young Gentleman of the Temple, left a Note in the Keyhole of his Chamber-door, thus, <hi>I am gone to the Devil; but if you cannot Read, carry it to the Stationers at the Gate, and he will do it for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>15.</label> A Rich Man, in the Countrey, who was never thought to be one of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s Off-ſpring, went with his Wife to ſee a Child of his at Nurſe; when he came, he very wiſely ask'd the Nurſe whether ſhe was a Maid or Married? ſhe reply'd ſhe was Married; ſays he, <hi>I'll have no Married Woman, I'll have a Maid to be my Child's Wet-Nurſe: Truly Sir;</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>then you had beſt beſpeak one at</hi> London, <hi>for we have no ſuch ready made here in the</hi> Countrey.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>16.</label> A Valiant Fellow who had been in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> was met by a Gentleman here, who ask'd him what Exploit he had done there? he anſwer'd, <hi>That he had cut off one of the Rebels Armes;</hi> the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135151:9"/> Gentleman reply'd, <hi>That it had been ſomething if he had cut off his Head: O</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you muſt conſider his Head was off before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>17.</label> When <hi>Metellus Nepos</hi> ask'd the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Roman</hi> Orator, in a jearing way, who was his Father? he reply'd, <hi>Your Mother has made that Question harder for you to Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>18.</label> A Rich Blade, that was a very great Eater, came to a Gentleman's Houſe to Court his Daughter: the Gentleman out of Civility, deſir'd him to ſtay and Dine with him, which he did, and Eat very heartily: after Dinner, he began to ſpeak to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy about the matter, and having ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd ſeveral Expreſſions of his Paſſion; he proteſted that he lov'd her as his own Soul; to whom ſhe wittily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, <hi>But not ſo well as your Body, Sir.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>19.</label> A Gentleman coming into <hi>London</hi> out of the <hi>Countrey,</hi> as he came by <hi>Stepny</hi> Church his Horſe threw him, which a young Gentlewoman ſeeing, fell a Laughing: the Gentleman being angry that ſhe jeer'd him, ſaid, <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admire</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:135151:9"/> 
                  <hi>not at this, Madam; my Horſe always ſtumbles when he ſees a Whore.</hi> To which ſhe anſwer'd merily, <hi>Have a care then, Sir; for if you ride into the City, you'll break your Neck.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>20.</label> A ſharping Scholar of <hi>King's Colledg</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> being in the Kitchin, and ſeeing the Cook take up a Plumb pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of the Pot, watching his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, while the Cook's back was turn'd; he whipt up the pudding into his own Chamber: which the Cook preſently miſſing, runs up into the Scholars Chamber, and search'd all about for it, but could not find it; the Scholar ſwore it was not in his Chamber (though the Cook ſmelt it) for he had ingeniouſly hung it out of his Window, which when the Cook was gone, he pull'd in, and eat as ingeniouſly</p>
               <p>
                  <label>21.</label> One deſiring a pretty Maid to go to a Gentleman and kiſs him, <hi>Nay Sir</hi> (ſays ſhe very wittily) <hi>I'le ne're go to Market for that Ware which I can have brought home to my Door.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>22.</label> At the Battel of <hi>Newport,</hi> the Prince
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135151:10"/> of <hi>Orange</hi> having the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and the Sea behind him, ſaid to his Souldies, <hi>Gentlemen, if you have a mind to live, you muſt do one of theſe two things; either eat thoſe Spaniards, or drink up this Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>23.</label> 
                  <hi>A</hi> London <hi>Scrivner dying in</hi> Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg, <hi>a merry Fellow writ thus over him:</hi> Know all men by theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, That I that have bound ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, am now bound faſt my ſelf, by a Gentleman of an Ancient Family, whoſe Name's Mr. <hi>Death,</hi> who brought me my laſt Sheet, and to my laſt full point. And though I was never Guilty of any great Wickedneſs, yet I often made many a blot, which my Daughter Pen was the occaſion of: I gave no bad Example to any, but good Copies to all: I was not unlearn'd neither, becauſe I always dealt in good Letters, and was a Juſtice of Peace in my own dominions; and though I could not hang (except an Arſe ſometimes, when my own money was to be Paid) yet I cou'd draw: I made all Bond-men but my Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for thoſe I made Free: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I had finiſh'd all my Letters, this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135151:10"/> Mr. <hi>Death</hi> threw ſome duſt upon 'em, and as I was making Bonds, aſſaulted me with Bills, and at laſt Seal'd the Letters of my Eyes quite up, and then ſent me away to my long-home.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>24.</label> A <hi>Welſh</hi>-man that was condemn'd to be Hang'd juſt before he was to be turn'd off, the Hang man ask'd him if he had any thing to ſay; he anſwer'd he had a deſire to ſpeak with ſome of his Countrey-men, before he died (if there were any there) ſo the Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man call'd to know if there were any there he ſhou'd hold up his Hand. It ſo happened that there was one there, ſo the Hang-man told him that the poor man wou'd ſpeak with him; ſo he drew near, and the <hi>Welſh</hi>-man ask'd him if he knew ſuch and ſuch in <hi>Wales,</hi> he replied he did; <hi>Then,</hi> ſays the <hi>Welſh</hi>-man, <hi>you know my Father and Mother, who I am certain will be very ſorrry to hear of my misfortune; but pray, to comfort them, tell them that I dye a very good Christian, and am inform'd that I ſhall go to Heaven, and I hope they will follow me thither the ſame way.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:135151:11"/>
               <p>
                  <label>25.</label> When <hi>Charles the Bald</hi> was Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and King of <hi>France,</hi> one <hi>Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Erigena</hi> a <hi>Scots</hi> man, for his great Learning had the honour to ſit at Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with the Emperour; but being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ungentiel in his behaviour, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ask'd him, <hi>Quid intereſt inter Scotum &amp; Sotum?</hi> Which in Engliſh is, <hi>What's the difference between a Scot, and a Sot?</hi> To which he readily, (but rudely) anſwer'd, <hi>Menſa;</hi> that is <hi>The Table:</hi> thereby calling the King Sot, by craft.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>26.</label> Another time this <hi>Johannes,</hi> who was but of little Stature, din'd at the King's Table, with two other Scholars who were tall men. The Emperor ſet him a Diſh with two great Fiſhes and one ſmall one, bidding him divide them between himſelf and the two Schollars; whereupon <hi>Johannes</hi> took the two large Fiſhes and laid them on his own Plate, and gave the ſmall one to the two Scholars. The Emperor ſmiling, ſaid, <hi>In faith Mr.</hi> Johannes <hi>you are no equal Divider: That's your Highneſſes mistake</hi> (ſaid he) and pointing to himſelf and the two great
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135151:11"/> Fiſhes, ſaid, <hi>Here are two great, and one little; and on the other ſide, is one little, and two great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>27.</label> One going in the dark, held both his Arms out to ſave his face, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accidentally againſt the door, which it ſeems ſtood ſlanting out, he hit his Noſe a good blow againſt it, <hi>Hey ho,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I never thought my Noſe was longer then my Arms till now; but if ever I go in the Dark again, I'le have a Candle in my hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>28.</label> A noted Countrey Gentleman blaming a Comicall Poet for bringing a leud debauch'd Ruffian on the ſtage, and ſo gave bad example to young men, <hi>Truly, Sir,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I brought ſuch a man on, but I hang'd him before he went off, and ſo gave them a good example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>29.</label> An Engliſhman and his Wife lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a Frenchmans houſe in <hi>Paris,</hi> the Engliſhman's Wife cried out in the night; ſo he ran up ſtairs to acquaint the midwife who lay there, of his wives condition, and went down to inform his Lanlord and Lanlady of it;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135151:12"/> ſo he ſtood by their bed ſide ſhivering in his ſhirt, for it was in a cold winter night; but could not ſpeak French, and ſo had much a do to make them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him; at laſt he did: his Landla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy pitying him, ſaid to her husband, <hi>Prethee, my Dear, let him come into Bed to us, and lye till day light, ſeeing it is ſo cold, and that he cannot in Civility go into his own Chamber; you need not fear any thing ſince you are in Bed with me:</hi> ſo he conſented to it, and the Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man came and lay down on the other ſide of the Woman; the Frenchman being tir'd ſoon fell faſt aſleep, the Engliſhman preſently grew warm, and began to careſs the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman; the motion of the bed, which was caus'd by their amorous engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wak'd her husband, he call'd out, <hi>Wife, Wife, what are you doing? Why what wou'd you have me do,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>if I ſhould ſpeak to him, you know he can't underſtand a word of our Language.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>30.</label> A Countrey Gentleman being at Dinner in <hi>London,</hi> with ſeveral Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of his acquaintance, one of them whoſe Name was <hi>Chambers,</hi> thinking to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135151:12"/> put a Joque upon him, ask'd him why he wou'd not live in <hi>London</hi> in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where he might find all ſorts of Company to fit his humour? <hi>I wou'd Sir,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if I cou'd find a Houſe fit for my turn.</hi> Says <hi>Chambers,</hi> I can help you to one that has three Rooms of a Floor, but 'tis built of Wood. Where is it, ſays the Gentleman? Says he, at Tyburn: <hi>'Tis true indeed,</hi> ſays the Gentleman, <hi>'tis a convenient Houſe, and ſtands in a good Air: for it will quickly Cure a Man of all Diſeaſes, and for a Houſe that is but one Story high, 'tis a very good one, and wants nothing in it but</hi> Chambers</p>
               <p>
                  <label>31.</label> An extravagant young Heir, having ſold all his Lands to maintain his Debauchery, fell Sick and ſent for a Phyſician; who perceiving that his Diſtemper aroſe from ill humours, contracted by his Intemperance, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd him to be let Blood, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſee it, he told him it was very green. <hi>Alas Sir,</hi> ſays he, <hi>how can it be otherwiſe, when I have Eaten up all my Meadows and Corn-fields.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>32.</label> A Doctor of Divinity, that had
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135151:13"/> a good Eſtate, and no Child, reſolv'd to make himſelf memorable to poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by ſome publick Charity; and ſo order'd a Cauſ-way to be made to a Market-Town, for the ſecurity of Travellers in the Fenny-Countrey. As the Labourers were at Work, the Doctor being there to overſee them, a Noble-Man came by, who had no great eſteem for Men of his Coat, and ſaid jearingly, <hi>Doctor, for all the Coſt you have been at, I don't think this is the way to Heaven. I am of your mind (quoth the Doctor) for then I cou'd not have expected to meet your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>33.</label> A Quaker being in Bed with his Wife, in the middle of the Night ſhe pull'd him, ſaying thus <hi>Awake,</hi> Eben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ezer, <hi>awake: What ſay'ſt thou the Wife of my Boſom,</hi> ſays he? <hi>Ariſe quickly,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>and go into the next Room, and nigh unto the place that pays Tribute to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>there ſtandeth a Wicker-Chair, thereon hangeth my Red Petticoat; take from thence two Farthings, and go to our Friend</hi> Theophilus <hi>the Tallow Chandlor, and buy therewith two Candels; light one of them, and ſpring in haſtily, for I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135151:13"/> fear our youngeſt Son</hi> Aminadab <hi>has B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t himſelf</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>34.</label> A Conſtable carrying a bigbelly'd wench before a Juſtice, ſaid to him; <hi>An't pleaſe your Worſhip I have brought you a maid with Child:</hi> whereupon the wench call'd him Fool and Knave; being reprov'd by the Juſtice, ſhe anſwer'd thus: <hi>Sir, this Conſtable muſt be one of them; for if I am a Maid, he is a Fool to think I can be with Child: and if I am not with Child, he is a Knave for ſaying ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>36.</label> Two Gentlemen quarrelling, the one gave the other a Challenge to meet him at a Six a Clock the next morning at ſuch a place upon his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: <hi>Hang Honour,</hi> ſays the other, <hi>for we both are but Worſhipful; and you know 'tis not my cuſtom, and I know 'tis not yours neither, to riſe before Eleven or Twelve a Clock; therefore pray let us conſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r whether we ſhou'd break our Reſt to break our Limbs.</hi> The other told him, <hi>If he did not meet him, he'd Poſt him:</hi> Well, ſaid he to him, <hi>if you do, I'll ride Poſt out of Town, and ſtay there till your furie's over.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:135151:14"/>
               <p>
                  <label>37.</label> An <hi>Oxford</hi> Scholar going along <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> was met by a huffing Fop, who thruſting between the wall and him, joſtl'd him almoſt to the Kennel, ſaying (with a no. Sir-Courtly-Face) <hi>I don't uſe to give the Wall to every Saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cey Loggerhead:</hi> To whom the Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, with Cap in hand, replied ſmartly, <hi>But I do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>38.</label> A Proper Tall Gentleman that had married a very little Woman to his Wife, being ask'd the reaſon of it, he replied, <hi>That of all Evils, it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the beſt to chooſe the leaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>39.</label> A Countrey man coming up to <hi>London,</hi> a little after the rebuilding of it, to ſee a Friend who made great Complaint of his own particular loſs, as well as of the loſs of ſo ſtately a City: <hi>As for your own loſs,</hi> ſays the Countrey man, <hi>I am very ſorry for it, but as for the Loſs of your City, I can't tell what to ſay; for who wou'd be troubled to have a good new ſuit for an old one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>40.</label> An Arch Wag ſpeaking of the late dreadful Fire of <hi>London.</hi> ſaid, <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non-ſtreet.</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:135151:14"/> roar'd, Wood-ſtreet was burnt to Aſhes, Bread-ſtreet was burnt to a Coal, Pie-corner was over-bak'd, and Snow-hill was melted down.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>41.</label> An old Gentleman was chid by a neighbour for marrying a young Girle; to whom he replied, <hi>She'll be a Woman to morrow; for,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Wives are young mens Mistreſſes, Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-ag'd mens Companions, and old mens Nurſes; and will you blame a man to have a Nurſe in his old Age?</hi> No, <hi>ſays he,</hi> I don't blame you for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Nurſe, but for your not Providing for Heaven; but that your Wife muſt do, <hi>for ſays he,</hi> Don't you know whither all Cuckolds go? O, ſays the old Gentleman, <hi>Now you put me in mind on't, 'tis true; for I have heard your Wife ſay ſome years ago, That ſhe was ſure her huſband wou'd go to Heaven; and now I find which way; and mum for that, my dear neighbour too.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>42.</label> A Highway-man being to be hang'd in a Countrey Town, Order was ſent to the Carpenter to make a Gallows; which he neglecting to do, the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135151:15"/> was forc'd to be defer'd, for which the Judge was not a little angry, who ſending for the Carpenter, ask'd him why he had not done it? <hi>Why Sir,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I have done two or three already, but was never paid for them; but had I known it had been for your Worſhip, I wou'd have left all other bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to have done it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>43.</label> One ask'd a Gentleman if he'd ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture any thing at the Lottery this Fair, and what he won, his Wife ſhou'd have for her fairing? <hi>No, ſays the Gentleman, for there's not one in forty has any luck but Cuckolds;</hi> which his ſweet Wife hearing, ſaid, <hi>Dear Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, Pray venture, for I'm ſure you'l have good luck.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>44.</label> A ſilly Fellow hearing a Lady's ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants call her <hi>Madam,</hi> at every word, he thought to be more mannerly then they, and therefore made an Addition of Miſtreſs to it, ſaying, <hi>Miſtreſs Madam, an't pleaſe your Ladiſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>45.</label> One that had a confounded Scold to his Wife, being continually tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the perpetual Clack of her
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135151:15"/> Tongue, wiſh'd one day, <hi>That ſhe was in Heaven;</hi> ſhe knowing thereby that he had a mind to be rid of her, in a great rage told him, <hi>She had rather ſee him hang'd firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>46.</label> A Lords Son in the <hi>North,</hi> that was much addicted to the Pleaſures of <hi>Venus,</hi> haunted all the pretty Girls thereabouts, but eſpecially one above the reſt, that was a very handſome Maid, and a Farmers Daughter who was his Father's Tenant; which gave him the more liberty of Courting her; and having Importun'd her very much, yet ſhe would not grant: At laſt he promis'd her Marriage, and thereby had the pleaſure of Enjoyment: But his Father and Mother fearing that he would make up a Match with the Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers Daughter, by going ſo often thither, ſent to another Lord that liv'd five Miles off, to Treat with him for his Daughter, who was a pretty Woman alſo, for his Son. So they ſoon agree'd, and the Marriage day was appointed, and the Young Blade was Riding with his Man to the Bride-Houſe; but the Farmer and his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had way laid him. The Farmer
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135151:16"/> ask'd him, <hi>What ſatisfaction he ſhou'd have for the wrong he had done his Daughter? Well,</hi> ſays he, <hi>There's forty Guinneys for you, and I'll give you a Bond, to make it up a hundred Pounds, to be paid in three Months, if you'll be contented.</hi> So the Bond was making under the Hedg, and the People at the Bride-Houſe admiring at his ſtay, ſent one to ſee; who when he came, found him Indenting with the Farmer and his Daughter under the Hedg. So when he had done, he Rid away to the Bride-Houſe as faſt as he could Gallop, and ſoon after was Married to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and when they were abed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he began to Kiſs her: <hi>Pray,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>reſolve me one Queſtion firſt: What made you under the Hedg with the Farmer &amp; his Daughter ſo long? Why,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that does not concern you at all. Well, ſays ſhe, I will know, or elſe you and I ſhall be at a diſtance: Why then,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if you won't be angry, I'll tell you. Well, I will not,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>let it be what it will. Why then,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I got the Farmers Daughter with Child, and ſhe was ſuch a Fool to tell her Father of it. So ſhe was by my Troth,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>for my Fathers Man got me with Child above a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135151:16"/> Twelvemonth ago, and you are the firſt that ever I told of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>47.</label> An Ignorant Fellow, having got in to be Reader in a Countrey-Church; the firſt Chapter of <hi>Mathew</hi> being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be Read, which contains the Genealogy, and is full of hard Names: He began with <hi>Abraham be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat Iſaac,</hi> and ſo read on three or four more, till he was quite nonplus'd; but cafting his Eyes forward, <hi>And ſo, ſays</hi> he, <hi>they beg at one another to the end of the Chapter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>48.</label> A Knight in <hi>Northampton-ſhire,</hi> that had three Sons, and no great Eſtate, told his youngeſt Son that he muſt needs bind him an Apprentice, and bid him chuſe his Trade. The Boy being of a ſmart and ingenious temper, told his Father he'd be a Tanner. Puſh, ſays he, that's a naſty Trade: That's true, ſays he; but yet 'tis the moſt convenient Trade for me of any; becauſe you have but a little to give me, and <hi>three Hides will ſet me up.</hi> What Hides are thoſe, ſays his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <hi>Why Sir,</hi> Reply'd the Boy, <hi>Yours and my two Brothers.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:135151:17"/>
               <p>
                  <label>49.</label> An Impudent Fellow having ſeveral Indictments brought againſt him, the Judge ſeeing the Notoriouſneſs of his Crimes, ſaid, <hi>Sirrah, if you ben't Hang'd, I'll be Hang'd for you:</hi> To whom the Rogue Reply'd, <hi>I thank your Honour, for your kind Offer; pray be not cut of the way when that time comes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>50.</label> A Gentleman of <hi>Lincoln's-Inn,</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Death of his Father, in the Countrey, was not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, as not knowing how he had left his Eſtate. An Intimate Friend of his ſeeing him, ſaid, <hi>Chear up,</hi> Jack; <hi>if your Father has left you a good Eſtate, you have no great cauſe to grieve; and if he has given you nothing, who'd grieve for ſuch a Father?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>51.</label> A Ranting Bully Drinking a Health to a Sober Man, he refus'd to Pledge him; upon which he wiſh'd this Curſe might light upon him, <hi>That in a dark and cold Rainy Night, he were ſet upon a tir'd Jade, bare Ridg'd, in a dirty Lane, with a Pocky Whore behind him, and his own Bones rotten, and ſeven Miles from any Houſe, not knowing one
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135151:17"/> ſtep of the way, and with never a Penny in his Purſe, both Hungry and Thirſty.</hi> Hold Sir, <hi>ſays the Man,</hi> there's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough already: I thank you for your good wiſhes; but hope in a little time you'll enjoy 'em all your ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>52.</label> An Arch Fellow in <hi>Oxford,</hi> took a great many Rams horns in his Basket, and went about the City with them, crying, <hi>Fair Cherries in Winter;</hi> this made many People call to him, and amongſt the reſt a Lawyer, who ſeeing his Ware, laught at him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, You fool, who do you think will buy your Horns of you? <hi>O Sir,</hi> repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he, <hi>Though you are provided, yet I may meet with ſome that are not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>53.</label> A Gentleman told his Cook that he would dine on a Veniſon Paſty, and ſo order'd him to provide one; which he did, with two or three other diſhes preliminary to it. So when the din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was ready, he brought it up in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; the firſt diſh was a good Surloin of Beef, which he ſet upon the Table before the Gentleman, which as ſoon as the Cooks back was turn'd, he took and threw out of the Window; then
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135151:18"/> the Cook brought up the ſecond Courſe, which was a Leg of Mutton and Colly-flowers, which he ſent out of the Window after the other; then the Cook brought up the Veniſon Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and threw it out of the Window, after the other two diſhes; which his Maſter ſtorming at him for, ask'd him the reaſon of it, ſays he, <hi>I thought your Worſhip intended to dine below, becauſe you ſent the diſhes down.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>54.</label> Two Perſons who had no great kindneſs for one another, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to dinner together with a Knight, who had a mind to be merry. Now they were both pretty witty; but one was ſlovenly, and the other ſpruce and neat: the ſpruce man was there firſt, and when the other came, he ran to the door to ſalute him and conduct him in, and thinking to make a Jeſt on his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courtly habit, ſtarted back, ſaying, <hi>I thought to have met a worthy Doctor; but I doubt in his ſtead I accoſt a Butcher.</hi> The Doctor (who very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood Repartee's) anſwer'd, <hi>Sir, I can't blame you for being ſurpriz'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis natural for horned Beaſts to dread the Butcher:</hi> which to one mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135151:18"/> under <hi>Capricorn,</hi> was a very cloſe Repartee.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>55.</label> One held a Paradox, that <hi>Wiſe men were the greateſt Lyers,;</hi> for ſays he, the Proverb ſays, <hi>Children and Fools ſpeak Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>56.</label> A certain Perſon ſpeaking unſeemly words before a Gentlewoman, ſhe ask'd him what Profeſſion he was of? <hi>Madam,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I'm a Civil Lawyer. Alas, Sir,</hi> replied ſhe then, <hi>If Civil Lawyers are ſuch rude People, I wonder what other Lawyers are.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>57.</label> 
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> being ask'd <hi>why he ſuffered ſo much brawling from his Wife:</hi> ſays he, <hi>Why do you ſuffer ſo much kackling of your Hens? Becauſe they lay Eggs,</hi> ſays he. <hi>And I from my Wife,</hi> reply'd <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, becauſe ſhe bears Children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>58.</label> At a Market Town in <hi>Sommerſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> there liv'd a Quaker that was a Barber, to whom the Parſon of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh came, demanding Fifteen Shillings of him for Tythe; The Quaker told him he ow'd him none, nor none wou'd he pay him: He told him 'twas his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135151:19"/> due, and if he wou'd not give it him by fair means, he'd make him do it by foul. The Quaker ask'd him for what it was due? he told him for Preaching and Reading Divine Service, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſterial Duties in the Church: Why, ſays the Quaker, I never came there: You might if you wou'd, ſays the Parſon, the Door ſtands open. Soon after the Quaker hearing that he was ſuing him for the money, enters an Action alſo againſt the Parſon for Fifteen Shillings: The Parſon hearing of it, went and ask'd him how he came to owe him Fifteen Shillings? he told him for Trimming: Why, ſays the Parſon, I was never Trim'd by you in my life: <hi>You might if you wou'd,</hi> ſays the Quaker, <hi>my Door ſtands open.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>59.</label> A Doctor of Phyſick in <hi>Oxford</hi> that us'd to ſalute every one he met, with theſe Words, <hi>I am very glad to ſee you well;</hi> A Student, a Gentleman of good quality, whom he ſo greeted, told him ingeniouſly, <hi>He believ'd he ly'd, for the World went</hi> ill <hi>with him when People were</hi> well.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:135151:19"/>
               <p>
                  <label>60.</label> One perſwaded a man to hang his Dog that had done ſome miſchief, <hi>I am loath to hang him,</hi> ſays he, <hi>but I'll go amongſt his Neighbours and give him an ill-name, and that's as bad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>61.</label> A French Captain having been a long time cloſely Beſieg'd in a place where for four Months he Eat nothing but Horſe-fleſh; at length being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, he repair'd to his former Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, thinking to enjoy the ſame dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances and careſſes that he was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſs'd with; But ſhe having been inform'd how he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d far'd ſince his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture; Hold, ſays ſhe, <hi>Monſieur;</hi> for though I have a mind <hi>to be gotten with Child,</hi> yet I'm reſolv'd <hi>never to be gotten with Colt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>62.</label> A covetous Tradeſman had a mind to be married, but was afraid of the charge of having Children too faſt; at laſt he reſolv'd to be married, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with his Wife that they wou'd lie together but once a Fortnight; and, ſays he, I intend to get every Fortnight a Joynt of the Child from Head to Foor; ſo by that device we ſhall not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135151:20"/> have too many Children: But I do it, my Dear, to eaſe thee in the bearing of 'em, which you know would be no ſmall trouble to you. After Marriage, it ſeems he lay with her the firſt night, and I can't tell how it came about, but at 40 weeks end ſhe was brought to bed of a brave Boy. Why how now Wiſe? ſays he, this is not according to my expectation: <hi>Yes Husband,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>but I may thank good Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or elſe for ought I know we might have had a Deform'd Child.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>63.</label> The King of <hi>Spain</hi> coming into one of his chief Cities, the Mayor came to make a ſpeech, and began thus: <hi>When the King of Peace rode to</hi> Jeruſalem; but being daſh'd out of Countenance, he ſaid again, <hi>When the King of Peace rode to</hi> Jeruſalem; and ſo the third time, but cou'd not proceed: Then the King turning to his Courtiers, ſaid, <hi>We may eaſily imagine this Man to be an Aſs by the Conſequent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>64.</label> Mr. <hi>Philemon Holland</hi> having Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated ſeveral Books, as <hi>Plutarch, Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Livy, Cambden,</hi> &amp;c. at length he Tranſlated <hi>Suetonius Tranquillus</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135151:20"/> Engliſh; upon which, an ingenious Blade writ this Diſtich on him:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Philemon <hi>with Tranſlations doth ſo fill us.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He will not let</hi> Suetonius <hi>be</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillus</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <label>65.</label> A Gentleman going into a Church in <hi>London,</hi> when they were chaunting <hi>Sternhold's</hi> and <hi>Hopkin</hi>'s Pſalms, which are not the moſt Melodious in the World, the Words were theſe, <hi>Have mercy upon us Miſerable Sinners: Ay,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>thoy might as well have ſaid, Have mercy upon us Miſerable Singers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>66.</label> Two Sparks ſtanding together in the <hi>Cloysters,</hi> ſeeing a pretty Lady paſs by, ſays one of them. <hi>There goes the handſomeſt Lady that ever I ſaw in my Life:</hi> She hearing him, turn'd back, and ſeeing him very ugly, ſaid <hi>Sir, I wou'd I cou'd in way of Requital ſay as much of you: Faith,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſo you may, and Lye as I did.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>67.</label>A Poor Man in <hi>Smithfield</hi> having a mind to Bind his Son to a Butcher; but being ſolicitous to get a Maſter of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135151:21"/> whom he might learn his Trade well, he ask'd his Friend, who was an Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Gentleman, and had great Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, to whom he ſhou'd Bind him? <hi>O,</hi> ſays he, <hi>there is a Phyſitian hard by you, Bind him to him; for he Kills more then all beſide in the Town.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>68.</label> A Gallant, Dining at a Friends Houſe, had promis'd a Lady to meet her in the Afternoon; but being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd after Dinner at Cards, cou'd not fairly get away; wherefore he call'd his Boy, and ſent him to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to Excuſe him; whiſpering him in the Ear, that what ever Anſwer the Lady return'd, he ſhou'd tell it him as if 'twere from a Man; that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany might not know. So the Boy went on his Errand, and a little after return'd to his Maſter, who ask'd him aloud before the Company, <hi>What was the Gentleman at home? Yes. Sir,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd the Boy: <hi>Well, what ſaid he to you; He ſaid, Sir, you might appoint any other time: What was he doing,</hi> ſays the Gentleman: <hi>He was putting on his Hood and Scarf, to go to Maſs,</hi> ſays the Boy, which diſcover'd the Intreague, and ſet them all a Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:135151:21"/>
               <p>
                  <label>69.</label> A Woman asking her Husband for ſome Money to buy a broad Silver and Gold Lace, to put on her Petticoat, he replied thus to her, <hi>If I once make you a</hi> Gold-finch, <hi>you will prove a</hi> Wag tail <hi>all your life after.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>70.</label> One that was a great Eater, fitting down to Supper, complain'd that he had loſt his Stomach. <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll,</hi> ſays a merry Fellow that was there, <hi>If a Poor Man has found it, he'll be utterly undone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>71.</label> A Biſhop being inform'd by his Steward of the greatneſs of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, that it was over proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his Eſtate; and that particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the number of his Servants was too great: the Biſhop order'd him to draw up a Note, of ſuch as were neceſſary, and ſuch as were not; which being done, he Summoned all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants together, and reading the Note, ſeparated them; and then ſaid, <hi>Theſe I have need of, and therefore they muſt continue; thoſe have need of me, and therefore they muſt continue alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:135151:22"/>
               <p>
                  <label>72.</label> Juſt after the late Kings Reſtaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when going to Church came to be in faſhion, an old Woman was advis'd by her Neighbours to go to Church; for fear of being Preſented, ſhe was reſolv'd to go once a Month to ſave her Bacon: So Dreſſing her ſelf very fine, ſhe came into the Church juſt at the Expiration of the Letany, and the Parſon having ſaid, <hi>Lord have Mercy upon us,</hi> and then the People Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto; ſhe Cry'd out aloud, <hi>I never was here before in my Life, and ſince you make ſuch a Wonder ment at it, I'll never come again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>73.</label> Two Gentlemen walking in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> in <hi>Oliver's</hi> time, ſaw the Sign of the <hi>Golden-Croſs;</hi> One of them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to lay two Bottles of Wine with the other, that he wou'd make the Maſter of the Shop pull down the Sign: The Wager being laid, he pulls off his Hat, and makes half a dozen Leggs to the Sign, firſt on one ſide, and then on t'other, which the Maſter of the Shop ſeeing, thinking to prevent his future ſuperſtition, ſuddenly pull'd down his Sign, whereby the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135151:22"/> won his two Bottles of Wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>74.</label> A Miniſter finding his Pariſhoners to be Ignorant, was reolved to Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and Inſtruct them at home; ſo going to an Ancient Womans houſe, amongſt other Queſtions, he ask'd her how many Commandments there were? She told him ſhe could not tell: He told her there were Ten: Whereat ſhe reply'd, <hi>A Jolly Company! God Bleſs you and them both together:</hi> Well, but Neighbour (ſays he) Do you think you can keep theſe Commandments? <hi>Ah! God Bleſs you, Sir,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>I am a Poor Woman, and can hardly keep my ſelf, I hope you will not put me to the Charge of keeping any of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>75.</label> Going to another of them, he ask'd her, who made her? She Replyed, She did not know: A Child ſtanding by, he ask'd him the ſame Queſtion, who Anſwer'd, GOD; whereupon the Parſon Reproving the old Woman, told her it was a ſhame that ſhe ſhould be ſo Ignorant, who had liv'd to thoſe Years, and that little Child could tell <hi>Marry,</hi> quoth ſhe, <hi>I am an old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135151:23"/> and have been made a great while, and he was made but t' other day; he may well tell who made him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>75.</label> A Quaker went to ſell a Horſe in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> a Chapman who look'd on the Horſe, complain'd of his Head; Quoth the Quaker, <hi>He that made that Head, won't learn of thee t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> make Heads.</hi> Why Friend, ſays the other, may I not ſpeak of thy Horſes faults if I ſee them? <hi>Nay,</hi> ſaid he <hi>for he ſees none in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, why ſhould'ſt thou ſee any in him.</hi> The Man was ſo taken with the bluntneſs of the Quaker, that he bought his Horſe; which, as he had told him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, was ſtark blind.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>76.</label> Two Gentlemen Riding on the Road, eſpied at a diſtance an old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man a doing her neceſſary occaſion, by a Hedg ſide; one of them offered a Bottle of Wine, that ſhe wou'd turn and ſee what ſhe had done; they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on the Wager, and ſhe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly did. Well, ſays the Loſer, I'll ask her why ſhe did ſo when I come to her; then Riding up to her, Well, good Woman, ſaid he, I ſee you have been Evacuating your ſelf; <hi>Do you ſo?</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:135151:23"/> quoth ſhe, <hi>you ſee no more with your Eyes, then you may carry away in your Mouth.</hi> But pray Mris. ſaid the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, what made you look back on it, when you had done? <hi>To ſee if there were enough for you Both, Sirs,</hi> reply'd ſhe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>77.</label> A young Eſquire, who had more Money then Wit, Traveling into <hi>Spain</hi> to a Univerſity, where a Man might be made a Doctor for Money, had a mind to take his Degrees; ſo for his better Reception, he invited the Doctor of the Chair to Supper, where being a little fluſh'd with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of his new Honour, he ask'd the Doctor if he wou'd take Money to make his Horſe a Doctor too? <hi>Yes,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I may make a Horſe a Doctor, as well as an Aſs; and ſo by conſiquence your Horſe as well as your ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>78.</label> An Impertinent Fellow told a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, that he was mad for doing a thing with leſs Judgment then he ought to have done, and that he ought to be ſent to <hi>Bedlam</hi> to be cur'd of Frenzie; and went on at that rate, till the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman wittily anſwer'd, <hi>That he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135151:24"/> as much, why (as in every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth there was provided a Bedlam for Madmen) there was never any place allotted for Fools.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>79.</label> A merry Archer coming into the Market on a Market day, neck'd an Arrow as if he intended to Shoot, and ſaid with a loud Voice, <hi>Now have at a Cuckold.</hi> A woman thinking he aim'd that way, and her Husband being by her, cries out, <hi>Stand away Husband, ſtand away Husband:</hi> Why you ſilly Jade (<hi>ſays he</hi>) I am no Cuckold, am I? <hi>No, no,</hi> (quoth ſhe) <hi>but who knows how a conſounded Arrow may glance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>80.</label> A Farmer in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> who for his Means was made a Knight, and his Wife thereby growing very Gallant and Fine; a Jocoſe Gentleman told his Worſhip, <hi>That he did not do well, in ſpoiling a</hi> Good Wife, <hi>to make a</hi> Mad-Dame.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>81.</label> A merry Gentleman ſeeing a great Diſh of Broth brought to the Table, with a little Chop of Mutton in the middle of it, began haſtily to unbut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton his Dublet; one asking him the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135151:24"/> meaning of it; <hi>I mean</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to ſwim through this Sea of Pottage, to that Iſland of Mutton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>82.</label> A merry Fellow Riding with his Maſter, he deſir'd to ask him a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; his Maſter knowing him to be a jocoſe witty Rogue, gave him leave: Why then, Sir, ſaid he, you ſee a Horſe and an Aſs yonder feeding toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; now ſuppoſe you were forc'd to be a Beaſt, which of thoſe two wou'd you he? You Fool, ſaid the Maſter, I wou'd be a Horſe, as being the nobler and more generous Creature: I'm of another Opinion, ſaid the Man, for I wou'd be an Aſs: His Maſter being pleas'd with the humour, ask'd his reaſon? <hi>Why,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I have often ſeen an Aſs Ride the Great Horſe, ſtrus briskly before his Company, be made a Juſtice, have the honour of Knighthood confer'd on him, and often Elected Mayor of a Corporation; but I never knew a Horſe capable of any of theſe Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>83.</label> An ignorant Countrey Fellow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing along <hi>Paternoſter-Row,</hi> had occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to change a Half-Crown into ſmall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135151:25"/> money, and looking over a Grate which which ſtood on the Stall, there ſat a large Monkey, whom he pray'd to change his money; the Monkey took it, and put it into the Till of the Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where he had obſerv'd money to be put, and then came and Grinn'd at the man; who being in a paſſion, made a noiſe at the Door, whereat the man of the Shop coming into the Shop, ask'd him what was the matter? <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I gave your Son half a Crown to change, and he will not give it me again, but Laughs at me, and will not give me one word of anſwer, tho I have asked him for it many a time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>84.</label> Two Friends meeting, one being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver joy'd to ſee the other, <hi>Hark you Sir,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Between you and I, my Wife's with Child. Faith,</hi> cry'd the other, <hi>you're a liar, for I have not ſeen her this twelve Months.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>85.</label> Two Perſons who had been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acquainted, but had not ſeen each other a great while, meeting on the Road, one as'kd the other how he did? he told him, He was very well, and was Married ſince he ſaw him: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther replyd, That was well indeed: Not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135151:25"/> ſo well neither, ſaid he, for I have Married a Shrew. That's ill, ſaid the other. Not ſo ill neither, ſaid he, for I had 2000 Pounds with her. That's well again, ſaid his Friend. Not ſo well neither, for I laid it out in Sheep, and they died of the Rot. That was ill indeed, ſaid the other. Not ſo ill neither, ſaid he, for I ſold the Skins for more money then the Sheep coſt. That was well indeed, quoth his Friend. Not ſo well neither, ſaid he, for I laid out my money in a Houſe and it was burn'd. That's very ill, ſaid the other. Not ſo ill neither, ſaid he, <hi>for my Wife was burn'd in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>86.</label> One that had been very much vex'd in Law-ſuits, went to <hi>Tyburn</hi> one day to ſee the Execution, and vow'd, <hi>That 'twas better to have to do with</hi> Tyburn, <hi>then</hi> Weſtminſter-Hall; <hi>for there Suits hang half a year, but at</hi> Tyburn <hi>half an hour's hanging ends all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>87.</label> A young Countrey Eſquire, who you muſt think never read <hi>Cook</hi> upon <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleton,</hi> &amp;c. had a mind to borrow ſome money privately, for which he was to give a Bond, and hearing it run,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135151:26"/> 
                  <hi>Be it known unto all men; Hey boys!</hi> ſays he, <hi>if all men muſt know it, then I'm ſure it will come to my Fathers Ear; therefore I'll have no ſuch Bond drawn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>88.</label> A Handſom young Widow having lately Buried an old grave Husband, call'd <hi>Old Symon,</hi> had been ſo us'd to a Bed-fellow, that ſhe cou'd not ſleep without one; but cou'd endure the thoughts of none but her dear Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; wherefore ſhe order'd a Carver to make her Husbands Statue as near as he cou'd; which every Night (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well warm'd) had a Shirt and Night-Cap put, on, and was laid by her in Remembrance of her Husband, that ſhe might, at leaſt, embrace him in Effigie. This trade had laſted ever ſince her Husband's Death, and ſhe wou'd not admit the Courtſhip of any Suiter; till at laſt a young Gentleman who was inflam'd with no ſmall paſſion for her, had by the help of his Wit, and ſome good Angels, prevail'd with her Maid to lay him one Night in the place of <hi>Old Symon:</hi> So the Widow came to bed to him, and caſting her hand over her dear Statue (as ſhe thought) ſhe felt a more agreeable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135151:26"/> warmth then uſual; nay, ſhe fancied 'twas alive and had motion; She was not frighted at it (which is not a little wonderful) but by degrees crept cloſer and cloſer to her Side-mate, till at length they were lock'd in Mutual Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces; by which ſhe with pleaſure found that it was not her Wooden Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow. In the Morning the Maid call'd at the Chamber-door, as ſhe us'd to do; Madam, what will you pleaſe to have for Dinner to Day? She reply'd, Roſt the Gooſe and the two Pheaſants that were brought in Yeſterday, Boyl a Leg of Mutton and Colly-flowers, and and get a good Diſh of Tarts and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards, and a Diſh of good dry'd Fruit. Madam, ſays the Maid, I think we have hardly Billets enough for a quick fire. <hi>You may burn Old Symon</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>burn Old Symon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>89.</label> A young Buxom Maid, that was newly Married to an old Man (by her covetous Father for money) was very melancholy; which a merry Fellow ſeeing, to comfort her, ſaid, <hi>Be of good Chear, my pretty dear Rogue, for an old Horſe will perform as good a Journey as a young one:</hi> She Smirking and Sighing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135151:27"/> ſaid, withal ſtroaking down her Belly, <hi>But not in this Road, Sir.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>90.</label> A Gentleman that was a Lawyer, coming up to <hi>London,</hi> to the Term, met a plain Countrey-man, and after the uſual Complement, of well met, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſays the Gentleman, Pray Friend an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me this Queſtion, <hi>Which are the greateſt wonders in the World?</hi> To which, after a little conſideration, he dryly Replyed, <hi>Women's and Lawyer's Tongues; for,</hi> ſays he, <hi>they always lye, yet never lie ſtill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>91.</label> A Gentleman Riding on the Road, overtook a young brisk Countrey Laſs, who after ſome time Travelling toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, conſented to his Amours; the man being conſcious of what he had done, and how Prejudicial it might prove to the Maid; told her, if any thing came of their Endeavours, ſhe ſhould hear of him at a certain place in <hi>London: 'Tis no matter Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>I am to be Married on</hi> Monday.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>92.</label> An old Woman in <hi>Southwark</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> was very civil in his Office, took an occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135151:27"/> him to the Parſon, whom ſhe had heard ſpeak of him: Prethee, Woman ſaid he, who was this <hi>Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Pilate,</hi> whom thou talk'ſt of? Quoth ſhe, How ſhould I know? I never was acquainted with any ſuch kind of People. The Parſon reprov'd her for her Ignorance, and bid her conſider and enquire againſt ſuch time ſhe ſaw him again: She being very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious in the matter, made the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and the next time ſhe ſaw the Parſon, ſhe told him that ſhe had found him out, and <hi>it was the little Oatmeal Man that came about with the white Horſe;</hi> the Parſon being amaz'd at ſo ſtrange an Imagination of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, ſhe cry'd out, <hi>What's the matter, Sir? I believe you don't know him your ſelf; but your Maid does, for I ſaw her buy a Pennyworth of Oatmeal of him, but two days ago.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>93.</label> Another ignorant old Woman in the Countrey hearing a Miniſter Preach on the Paſſion of Chriſt, of the Cruel and Barbar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Death that the Jews put him to, wept grievouſly; and when the Miniſter had done, ſhe came to him, and ask'd him how long
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135151:28"/> it was ſince this ſad thing was done? The Miniſter told her it was ſixteen-hundred Years ſince: <hi>O then,</hi> ſays the Woman, being a little revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>if it be ſo long ago, I hope in God it mayn't be true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>94.</label> A brisk young Woman, going to her Husbands Funeral, a Gentleman comes and whiſpers her in the Ear, profering his Service in way of Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: She thank'd him very kindly, but told him, <hi>He came too late; for,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>I was Yeſterday made ſure to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>95.</label> A Citizen Travelling into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, came into a very good Inn, where the Maſter of the Houſe was Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to him, ſhowing all his conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies; which were ſo far beyond the common Inns, that he told him, <hi>It was a Houſe for a Nobleman;</hi> at which the Inn-keeper fell into a great paſſion, calling him Raskal, and abuſive Fellow. The Gentleman not being pleas'd with his Entertainment, went to the next Houſe in the ſame Town; where telling his Hoſt the buſineſs, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd him, <hi>That the Man had lately
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135151:28"/> Broke, and Paid but a Noble in the Pound of his Debts, which had Enabled him to Build that ſpacious Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>96.</label> An Amorous Gentleman in <hi>Paris,</hi> Playing under his Miſtriſſes Window with a Lute, ſhe commanded her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to throw ſtones at him, which he took in good part, and eſteem'd as a great Grace, fancying himſelf like <hi>Orpheus;</hi> ſaying, <hi>The Stones danc'd af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Muſick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>97.</label> A Wine-Cooper in <hi>Mark-Lane</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Gentleman down into his Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to Treat him, he finding no Seat there for him to ſit on, ask'd him the reaſon of it: <hi>Why,</hi> ſays the Wine-Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>I will have no Man here Drink lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then he can ſtand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>98.</label> A Citizen of <hi>London</hi> had for a long time been Jealous of his Wife, miſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting her Chaſtity, but had no real proof of it; till at length he reſolving to have an Ocular Demonſtration, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to go into the Countrey, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns the ſame Night; and coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Houſe, looks through the Door into his Wives Chamber, and ſees a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135151:29"/> brisk Spark Careſſing her in an Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous manner. Having thus ſatisfied his curioſity, he retires, reſolving to diſcipline her the next day; ſo he comes to her, and after ſome little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, taxes her with the laſt Nights Recreation. She denies it, and he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it, telling her that he ſaw it with his own Eyes; to which ſhe wittily and ſimperingly ſaid, <hi>What my Dear! Won't you believe your own dear Wife, before your own Eyes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>99.</label> Two young Fellows obſerving a Countrey man go up into the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, went up after him, and when they came to the top, they bound him, and pickt his Pocket; which as ſoon as ever they had done, they hear'd ſome body coming up; ſo being put to their ſhifts, and in ſome danger of diſcovery, they made haſte down, and meeting a Man, they told him, There was a pleaſant Scene acting at top, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a young Maid and her Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heart; ſo the Man believing them, and being a merry Fellow, went down with them; ſaying, <hi>That if he could make no ſport, he was reſolv'd to ſpoil none;</hi> and ſo by this witty Stratagem the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135151:29"/> Rogues eſcap'd with the money, and the poor Countrey-man was left to be reliev'd by the next comer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>100.</label> An old Baud being brought before a Juſtice of Peace, in <hi>London,</hi> for kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a Baudy-Houſe, and being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd by ſeveral Witneſſes, and upon probable Grounds, the Juſtice ſaid in a Paſſion to her, <hi>You Old Hag, you do keep a Debauch'd Houſe, and I will maintain it:</hi> whereupon the old Jade dropt him a Cour'ſy, ſaying, <hi>I moſt humbly thank your Worſhip, I deſire no better Warrant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>101.</label> A Tinker coming through <hi>Cornhill,</hi> and ſounding briskly on his Kettle, <hi>Have you any Work for a Tinker?</hi> A Grocer that thought to put a Jeſt upon him (there being a Pillory near his Door) bid him ſtop thoſe two Holes, pointing to the Pillory; to whom the Tinker ſmartly reply'd, <hi>Sir, if you will lend me your Head and Ears, I will find a Hammer and Nails, and give you my Work into the bargain.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:135151:30"/>
               <p>
                  <label>102.</label> A modeſt Gentlewoman being forc'd by her Mother to accuſe her Husband of Defect, ſhe deſir'd the Judge, being in Court, that ſhe might Write her mind for Modeſties ſake. So the Judge granted her requeſt, and order'd Ink and Paper to be given her; ſo ſhe took the Pen without dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it into the Ink, and made as if ſhe wou'd Write; ſays one of the Counſellers to her, <hi>Madam, there's no Ink in your Pen. Truly Sir,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>that's just my Caſe, and therefore I need not Explain my ſelf any further.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>103.</label> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> coming into a School in <hi>London,</hi> and ſeeing a very part Boy, ask'd him how often he had been Whipt? To whom he Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onſly anſwer'd in the words of <hi>Aeneas</hi> to Queen <hi>Dido,</hi> 
                  <q>Infandum Regina jubes renovare do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorem.</q> For which ſhe gave him a Reward.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>104.</label> Another time the Queen coming into <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-School, had ſome Verſes made to her <hi>Extempore,</hi> by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oor Boy; and being pleas'd with his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135151:30"/> quickneſs, ſhe bid him make ſome Verſes upon this, <hi>Pauper ubique jacet,</hi> which he did preſently as follows:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>In Thalamis Reginatuis hac nocte Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerem,</l>
                  <l>Si verum hoc eſſet, pauper ubique jacet:</l>
               </lg>
               <p>For which the Queen took ſpecial notice of him, and gave him great preferment afterwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>105.</label> A Gentleman being in Mourning for his Father, was Riding out with ſome fine Ladies, who ſeeing his Horſe have a Velvet Saddle, and Embroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd Cloath, ask'd him why that was not black too? <hi>O,</hi> ſays the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>my Horſes Father is not dead yet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>106.</label> A Countrey Farmer coming up to <hi>London,</hi> had a Token to deliver to his Landlord's Son, a young Gentleman of the Temple: when he came to his Chamber, he found a Note in the Key-hole, written, <hi>I am gone to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil;</hi> whereupon the poor Farmer fell into a great fright, having the ſaddeſt apprehenſions imaginable. Alas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaid he, that ever my Landlord ſhou'd
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135151:31"/> ſend his Son to this wicked place; a fine young Gentleman that has coſt his Father many a fair Pound to bring him up to Learning, and that ever he ſhou'd come to this Ungodly Town, in two or three Months time to go to the Devil; I dare not carry this ſad evil Tydings to his Father: And as he was making theſe ſad Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a young Student camp up and told him, that the Note only meant the Devil-Tavern hard by, and that he believ'd he might find him there. So he went thither, and found the Gentleman, and preſented his Father's Token, and then told him the Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary trouble he was in, upon Reading the Note. At which the Gentleman Laugh'd heartily, and gave the Farmer ſuch an Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that when he came down into the Countrey, he told his Friends, <hi>That he never far'd better in his Life, then he did at the Devil;</hi> which put them all into no ſmall Aſtoniſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>107.</label> A Scholar of <hi>Oxford,</hi> having wore out the Heels of his Boots, brought them in his hands to a Cobler, and ſhewing him them, ſaid, <hi>O thou curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135151:31"/> Artificer, that haſt by no ſmall pains and study, arriv'd to the perfection of that exquiſite Art of reparing the defects of old decayed Calcuments, affix me two Semicircles to my Suppeditors:</hi> The Cobler ſtar'd upon him, as if he wou'd have look'd him through; but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle recovering himſelf, ſaid, <hi>Before George, Sir, I underſtand not your hard Language; but if I put on two Heel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces, I'll have a Groat for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>108.</label> The ſame Scholar being ask'd by a Porter for a Gentlemans Chamber in the Colledg, he directed him thus, <hi>You must crncifie the Quadrangle, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend the Grades, and you will find him perambulating in his Cubicle, near the Feneſter.</hi> Pray Sir, ſays the Porter, what is that <hi>Feneſter? It is,</hi> replies the Scholar, <hi>the Diaphanous part of an Edifice, erected for the Introduction of Illumination;</hi> which ſo amaz'd the Porter, that at firſt he did not know what to think, till recovering himſelf, he went and enquir'd of another, who gave him plainer directions, in more intelligible terms.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:135151:32"/>
               <p>
                  <label>109.</label> An old Uſurer dying, left a good Eſtate to his Son, who was more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh in the ſpending of it, then his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had been careful in ſcraping it up: As this young Spark was Riding in his Coach to <hi>Epſome,</hi> he was angry whith his Coachman, for not driving faſter, calling to him, ſaying, You Dog, if you don't make more haſte, I'll come and Kick you to the Devil: <hi>Sir,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Coachman, <hi>I ſwear if you do, I'll there t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll your Father how Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagantly you have ſpent his Eſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>110.</label> A Gentleman living in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, having ſome urgent buſineſs at <hi>London,</hi> and his Lady at the ſame time being ready to Lye-in, leaves order with his Servant, a Welſhman, that when his Lady was Delivered, if it were a Son, he ſhould come to <hi>London,</hi> and acquaint him, promiſing him for his paines a new Suit of Cloaths; the Lady was in a ſhort time after Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered of a Daughter; however <hi>Jack</hi> (unwilling to loſe his Suit of Cloaths) goes to <hi>London</hi> and acquaints his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that his Lady was brought to Bed of a brave young Son; the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135151:32"/> being over-joy'd at the News, perform'd his Promiſe, and <hi>Jack</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well accoutred, returns to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs: and in a ſhort time after, the Gentleman returns; and meeting his Wife, wiſheth her much Joy of her Son; but ſhe alleadging it was a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and he finding himſelf abuſed, orders <hi>Jack</hi> to be ſent for; who when he came, ſtill continued in his former ſaying, that it was a Son; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Child was produced, and ſhown to the whole Company; <hi>Jack</hi> ſtill avers it to be a Son; why thou Fool, quoth the Nurſe, if it were a Son it ſhould have a Cock here <hi>Cots<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plut,</hi> quoth the Welſhman, is hur in haſte? Would hur have a Cock there already? Let hur keep hur till hur is ſixteen or ſeventeen years old, and if hur have no Cock then, Hang hur.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>111.</label> A brisk young Lady, ſeeing the Sheriff of a County, who was a come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly young Man, wait upon the Judge, who was an old Man, was ask'd by one, which ſhe had moſt mind to, the Judge, or the Sheriff? She anſwer'd, The Sheriff. He asking the reaſon, ſhe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135151:33"/> replied, <hi>That ſhe lov'd Judgment well, but Execution much better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>112.</label> Some Soldiers in the Camp being very Lowſy, complain'd to their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, who being a Jocoſe man, bid them turn their Shirts and ſhake them, telling them that the Lice wou'd have a days March at leaſt, before they cou'd come to their Skin.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>113.</label> A Handſom Countrey Maid coming to <hi>Croyden</hi> Market, and being very nimble, leap'd off her Horſe, but the Pummel of her Saddle being high, catcht hold of her Petticoat, &amp; ſhew'd almoſt all that Nature gave her; which a Gentleman ſtanding by and ſeeing, ſaid, Sweetheart, you have a very clear Skin, To whom ſhe anſwer'd briskly, <hi>Sir, if you like it ſo well, why did not you come and Kiſs it, to take your leave on't, for you are not ever like to ſee it again?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>114.</label> Two Scots-men meeting about Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-time, one ask'd the other to lend him Six-pence; by my Troth, quoth he, I have but a Groat; <hi>Prethy mon,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>lend me that, and I will truſt you for the other Twa-pence.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:135151:33"/>
               <p>
                  <label>115.</label> A young Woman having Married a great Student, who was ſo intent on his Studies, that ſhe thought her ſelf too little regarded by him, and one day when they were at Dinner with ſome Friends, ſhe wiſh'd her ſelf a Book, that ſhe might have more of her Husbands Company; <hi>If it muſt be ſo,</hi> ſays her Husband, <hi>I wiſh thou wer't an Almanack, that I might change thee for a new one once a Year.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>116.</label> A Gentleman alighting out of his Coach at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> ask'd a Foot-man that ſtood there, what a Clock it was: Sir, ſays the Footman, what will you give me? Why, replied the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, muſt I give you any thing to tell me that? <hi>Yes Sir,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>for we Courtiers do nothing without money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>117.</label> Two Gentleman diſcourſing over a Glaſs of Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, of the Affairs of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and of the ſeveral Claſſes of men therein; One of them wittily ſaid, <hi>That in it there were neither Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars enough, Gentlemen enough, nor Jews enough.</hi> I can but admire at your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in that, ſays the other Gentleman;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135151:34"/> for methinks, there are rather too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe ſorts, then too few: To which he replied, <hi>If there were Scholars enough, ſo many wou'd not be double or treble benefic'd; If Gentlemen enough, ſo many Peaſants wou'd not be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Gentry; And if Jews enough, ſo many Chriſtians wou'd never profeſs <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>118.</label> A Conceited Scholar, that was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come from <hi>Oxford,</hi> Drinking with two or three Gentlemen at the <hi>Mitre-Tavern</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> was very brisk and airy, and wou'd needs be forming of Sylogiſms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> One wiſe one was this, He bid them fill two Glaſſes of Wine, which they did: Now, ſays he, I will prove thoſe two Glaſſes to be three, thus, Is not here one, ſays he? Yes, ſays the Gentleman. And here another, that's two, ſays he: Yes, ſays the Gentleman again. Why then, ſays he, one and two is three, ſo 'tis done. <hi>Very well,</hi> ſays the Gentleman, <hi>I'll have one Glaſs, and that Gentleman ſhall have the other, and you ſhall have the third for your pains in finding it out.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:135151:34"/>
               <p>
                  <label>119.</label> One who had layn with his Female Servant, the next day ask'd her how many Commandments there were? She anſwer'd nine: Thou Fool, quoth he, haſt thou liv'd to this Age, and knoweſt no better? There are ten. <hi>I I know,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>very well, there were ten Yeſterday; but you and I broke one of them the laſt Night, ſo that there are but nine of them left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>120.</label> A witty, though unfortunate Fellow, having tried ſeveral Trades, and fail'd in them all, at laſt took an Ale-houſe, and ſet up the Sign of the Shirt; Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting under it, <hi>This is my laſt Shift;</hi> which witty Device, brought him much Company and Profit.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>121.</label> A Gentleman that had never been us'd to Wounds, receiv'd a ſmall Scratch with a Sword in a Tavern-Frav; at which he was ſadly frighted, and ſent immediately for a Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who coming, and ſeeing the Wound but ſlight, and the Gentleman in a great fear; for Sport's ſake pretended great danger, and therefore ſends his Man with great ſpeed to fetch him
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135151:35"/> ſuch a Plaiſter: <hi>Why Sir,</hi> quoth the Gentleman, <hi>is the Wound ſo dangerous? O Yes,</hi> reply'd the Arch Chyrurgeon, <hi>for if he don't make great haſte, it will heal of it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>122.</label> A Woman in the Countrey that had Ten Children, told her Husband that <hi>Nine of them were his, and no more;</hi> now he miſtruſting the Parſon of the Pariſh had been ſweet upon her, ſaid, <hi>Well, Wife, I'll keep the Nine, but I never deny'd the Clergy their due, and ſo will not begin now; for the Parſon ſhall have the Tenth for his Tythe, it being rightly due to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>123.</label> A Countrey man coming through <hi>Cheapſide</hi> with Hob-nails in his Shoes, and treading in a ſlippery place, his Heels flew up; which a Citizen taking notice of in his Shop, ſaid to the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <hi>How now, Friend? You ſee our Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtones are ſo proud, they ſcorn to let a Countrey-Clown tread on them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hah!</hi> ſays the Countrey man, <hi>as proud as they are, I made them kiſs my Arſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>124.</label> A <hi>Welſhman</hi> that was condemn'd to be hang'd, had the benefit of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135151:35"/> granted to him, and ſo was burnt in the Hand; which when it was doing, they bid him ſay, <hi>God bleſs the King: Nay,</hi> ſays he, <hi>God bleſs hur Father and Mother; for if they had not taught hur to read, hur might have been hang'd for all the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>125.</label> A huffing Young Blade coming to <hi>Epſom,</hi> call'd an honeſt plain Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that was there to hold his Horſe: <hi>Can one hold him,</hi> ſays he; <hi>Yes, yes,</hi> ſays the Gallant: <hi>Then you may do it your ſelf,</hi> ſays the Countrey man, and ſo went away.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>126.</label> A Countrey man that was very ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, coming to the Arch-Biſhops Houſe with his Rent, the Arch-Biſhop coming through the Hall, ask'd who 'twas? <hi>An't pleaſe your Worſhips Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> ſays the Countrey man, <hi>I am come to pay you your Rent;</hi> ſo the Arch-Biſhop went out; and the Servants told him, he muſt ſay, <hi>An't pleaſe your Grace;</hi> But the Arch-Biſhop coming in again, he was at, <hi>An't pleaſe your Worſhip's Honour:</hi> they told him he muſt ſay <hi>Grace; Muſt I ſo?</hi> ſays he; then putting his Hat before his Eyes, he ſaid, <hi>The Eyes of all things,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:135151:36"/>
               <p>
                  <label>127.</label> A Gentleman reproving his Friend that was a married man, for getting a maid with Child, ſaying, He admir'd that ſuch a man as he wou'd defile his Bed ſo: <hi>You miſtake, Sir,</hi> ſays he, <hi>there was no defiling of my Bed in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Caſe, for I did it in the Fields.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>128.</label> A conceited Fellow, that had an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary good opinion of himſelf, ask'd his Friend what others thought of him? <hi>Why,</hi> ſays his Friend, <hi>The Wiſe think you fooliſh, and Fools think you wiſe; Now pray what think you of your ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>129.</label> Two Gentlemen that had been a great while at Law together, and had ſpent a great deal of Money at it, one of the Gentlemens Friends told him, That his Antagoniſt had remov'd his Suit into Chancery; <hi>Let him remove it into H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I don't queſtion but to get a Lawyer to follow it for money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>130.</label> An Engliſh Merchant at <hi>Lisbon</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> ſold ſome Jews five hundred pounds worth of Gloves; but they falling off from their Bargain, would
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:135151:36"/> have but half of them: Well, ſaid the Merchant, you muſt give me ſome time to ſort them, and then you ſhall have half; ſo he order'd his Man to put all the Right-handed Gloves in one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and the left-handed ones in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Then when the Jews came, he bid them take their choice; which when they had done, and were pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them up, they perceiv'd them to be all for one hand; and ſo were glad to take the other parcel at the Merchants own rate.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>131.</label> One ſtanding in the Pillory at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and his Wife being by him to bear him Company, a Gentleman that ſaw him, ſaid, <hi>He believ'd he was a Papiſt, becauſe he had his Croſs with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>132.</label> Another man hearing a Parſon Preach on that Text, <hi>Take up your Croſs and follow Me;</hi> took his Wife on his Back the next Sunday, and came into the middle of the Church, while the Parſon was preaching, and looking up to him, ſaid, <hi>Now Sir, I have brought my Croſs, what muſt I do with it?</hi> The Miniſter being a little ſurpriz'd
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135151:37"/> at the humour of the Fellow, hardly knew what to ſay to him, but at laſt he bid him ſet it down there: <hi>Yes, that I will;</hi> ſays he, <hi>with all my heart, though it were in the middle of the Sea: But I ſee,</hi> ſays he, <hi>as well as you pretend to love the Croſs, mine may lie upon my hands this forty Years, before you'll eaſe me of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>133.</label> A Gentleman ask'd one of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Sex, <hi>Whether ſhe was Maid, Wife, or Widow;</hi> and bid her tell him truly: She being a little put to it, after ſome conſideration upon this hard queſtion, and being above twenty years old, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him thus, <hi>Though I was never married, Sir, yet you may write me down Young Woman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>134.</label> King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, going once to <hi>Graveſend,</hi> took <hi>Will. Summers</hi> his Jeſter with him for his diverſion; the Wind being very high, it was very tempeſtuous; and <hi>Summers</hi> being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fearful, thought himſelf in great danger, and ſaid to the King, <hi>Harry, Harry, I had rather be thy Fool by Land, than thy Companion by Water:</hi> At which the King laugh'd heartily.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:135151:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <label>135.</label> A Nobleman having a mind to be merry, ſent for his Chapl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in, and told him, That unleſs he could reſolve him theſe Three Queſtions, he ſhould be diſcarded, and turn'd out of his Service; but if he cou'd, he ſhou'd have Thirty Guinneys, and the beſt Horſe in his Stable: So he propos'd the Queſtions to him, which were theſe; <hi>Firſt, What compaſs the World was about? Secondly, How deep the Sea was? And Thirdly, What he thought?</hi> The Poor Chaplain was in a peck of Troubles, and did not know how to anſwer them, or what to ſay, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them very unreaſonable Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſo that all he could do was to deſire a little time to conſider upon them, which the Earl granted. So he going along the Fields one day very melancholy, a Cobler of the Town, a merry Fellow (who was very like the Chaplain, both in Phyſiognomy and Stature) met him, and ask'd him the reaſon of his Sadneſs; which with ſome Reluctancy he told him: O Sir, ſays the Cobler, don't be dejected, chear up; I've thought of a device to ſave your Place, and get you the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135151:38"/> and Horſe too; but you ſhall give me Ten Guinneys for my pains. So he agreed to't; and it was thus: Says he, I'll put on your Cloaths, and go to my Lord, and anſwer his Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Accordingly he went, and when he came before him, he anſwer'd him thus: To the firſt Queſtion, <hi>What Compaſs the World was about?</hi> He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, <hi>It was four and twenty hours Journey; and if a man could keep pace with the Sun he might eaſily go it in that time.</hi> To the ſecond, <hi>How deep the Sea was?</hi> He anſwer'd, <hi>Only a ſtones throw; for caſt it into the deepeſt place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f it, and in time it will come to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom.</hi> To the third, (which I fancy your Lordſhip thinks the moſt difficult to be Reſolv'd, but is indeed the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt) which is, <hi>What your Lordſhip thinks?</hi> I anſwer, <hi>That you think I am your Chaplain, when as indeed I am but the Cobler of Glouceſter.</hi> The Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was ſo pleas'd with his witty An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, that he perform'd his Promiſe to his Chaplain, and gave the Cobler Ten Guinneys for his Ingenuity.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>136.</label> Says a Glazier to a Painter, <hi>I ſee you do all under a Colour. Get you gone, you
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:135151:38"/> Rogue,</hi> reply'd the Painter, <hi>you're al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways picking of Quarrels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>137.</label> A Certain King kept a Fool in his Court, that us'd to write down in a Book, all the Follies of the great Men in the Court; which Book the King ſometimes, when he was diſpos'd to be Merry, wou'd look into. Now one day after Dinner, the King read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Book, found himſelf in it, with a Story of five-thouſand Pounds, which he gave a <hi>Jew</hi> in his Court, to go to <hi>Barbary</hi> and buy Horſes with: So the King ask'd his Jeſter, why he put him in? <hi>Why,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for giving your Money to one that you may never ſee again:</hi> But ſays the King, What if he ſhould return and bring the Horſes, what Folly is it then? <hi>Why, if he do's,</hi> replied the Fool, <hi>I'll blot out your Name, and put in his, for a Fool, for not keeping your Money when he had it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>138.</label> Two Women ſcolding in the Street, another of their Acquaintance came by, whom they wou'd refer their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to; <hi>No,</hi> ſays the Woman, <hi>pray Excuſe me, I won't meddle in it, but will ſtand Neuter: How can that be,</hi> ſays
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:135151:39"/> one of them, <hi>when you have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the Town?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>139.</label> Doctor <hi>Fuller,</hi> overtook one Mr. <hi>Woodcock</hi> upon the Road, falling into Diſcourſe in a facetious manner, ask'd him what difference there was between a Woodcock and an Owl, (ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Mr. <hi>Woodcock</hi> had not known him) He wittily replied, <hi>That an Owl was Fuller in the Head, Fuller in the Face, Fuller in the Eyes, Fuller in the Neck, and Fuller all over.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>140.</label> A Scholar meeting a Countreyman upon the Road, Rid up very briskly to him; but the Countreyman out of Reſpect to him, was turning off his Horſe to give him the Road, when the Schollar laying his Hand upon his Sword, ſaid, <hi>'Tis well you gave me the Way, or I'd—What wou'd you have done?</hi> ſaid the Countreyman, holding up his Club at him: <hi>Given it you Sir,</hi> ſays he, pulling off his Hat to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>141.</label> One Reading in the Famous Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the ſeven Champions, how St. <hi>George</hi> kill'd the Dragon, and ſav'd <hi>Sabra</hi> the fair Maid of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſaid,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:135151:39"/> 
                  <hi>He admir'd how Men cou'd invent ſuch Lies; for,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I believe there never was any ſuch Dragon, or ſuch a Man as St.</hi> George. <hi>O,</hi> ſays another, <hi>I can believe that, better than that there was a Maid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>142.</label> A Tallow-Chandler dying, a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Fellow ſaid, <hi>He wonder'd, that he that had made ſo many Weeks, cou'd make his Life no longer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>143.</label> A Luſty young Man, in <hi>Somer ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> after he had been Married about four Months, grew very Lean and Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo that he cou'd hardly crawl a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long; He one day ſeeing a Butcher run over a Plough'd Field after a Mad-Bull, ask'd him the reaſon of it) Why, ſays the Butcher, it is to Tame him: <hi>O,</hi> ſays the Fellow, <hi>Let him be Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, let him be Married; if that don't Tame him, I'll be hang'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>144.</label> A Soldier, a merry. Fellow, finding a Louſe on his Sleeve, walking to take the Air, took him up by the Back, and ſaid, <hi>I ſwear, if I catch you again out of your Quarters, you ſhall be Hang'd; and ſo put him into the Collar of his Doublet.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:135151:40"/>
               <p>
                  <label>145.</label> A certain Highway-man having committed a Robbery in <hi>Devon-ſhire,</hi> was taken in <hi>Dorſet-ſhire,</hi> making to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>London,</hi> and brought before a Juſtice of Peace, who wou'd not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with him, but wou'd ſend him back into the Shire where he committed the Robbery; which a witty Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey man hearing (that had been at the trouble of taking him, and was unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to Guard him back into the other County) deſir'd leave to ask the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice one Queſtion, which he granted: <hi>Why then,</hi> ſays the Man, <hi>I deſire your Worſhip to tell me, if a Man be taken abed with your Wife to Night, whether he muſt be ſent thither again the next Night?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>146.</label> A Gentleman order'd a Crane for Supper; but his Cook having a Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heart in a longing condition, cut off a Leg and ſent her; ſo the One-Legg'd Crane was ſet on the Table, which the Gentleman ſeeing, was enrag'd at his Cook; but he being an arch Wag, readily told the Gentleman, that Cranes had but one Leg; and avow'd it with that confidence, that he gain'd upon his wiſe Maſters belief; but he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135151:40"/> reſolving to obſerve it as he was walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Fields one Froſty-Morning, he ſaw a flock of Cranes, and ſending for his Cook, they held up one of their Legs under their Wings, as is the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of thoſe birds in the cool wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>So,</hi> ſays his Cook, <hi>I hope your Worſhip is ſatisfied that they have but one Leg;</hi> but the Gentleman going pretty near to them, cries <hi>Cuſh,</hi> and frighted them up, whereupon both legs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd; <hi>Look,</hi> ſays the Gentleman, <hi>they have now two Legs: Oh,</hi> ſays the Cook, <hi>if you had cried Cuſh to that in the Diſh, it wou'd have had two Legs too.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>147.</label> A Gentleman loſing his Watch, Complain'd to his Friend of his loſs; <hi>Alas, Sir,</hi> ſays he, <hi>all the World can't help it, Time will away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>148.</label> A Bully meeting a brisk Lady in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park, with her naked Breaſts appearing very tempting, ſays to her, <hi>Madam, is that Fleſh to be ſold? No,</hi> replied ſhe, <hi>no money ſhall buy it: Then,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Madam, if you won't ſell your Ware, I'd wiſh you to ſhut up your Shop: Faith, Sir,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>you may be ſure I'll never let you come within my
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135151:41"/> Doors: 'Tis no matter, Madam,</hi> replied he, <hi>for I am ſure they are wicked ones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>149.</label> A Perſon of Quality in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, keeping a Baboon at his Door with a handſom fine Coat on; a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Fellow brought a Letter and gave it to the Baboon, who tore it to pieces; and the Lord happening to come out, ſaw him do it; at which he was angry with the Fellow, and ask'd him why he deliver'd it not to him himſelf? <hi>Why,</hi> ſays the Fellow, <hi>I gave it to your Son, and he tore it: You Fool,</hi> ſays he, <hi>'tis a Baboon: Indeed,</hi> ſays the Fellow, <hi>I thought it was your Son, he is ſo like you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>150.</label> A Woman having a mind to oblige her Husband, deſir'd him to invite ſome of his Friends to Dinner, and they wou'd be merry, for, ſays ſhe, I have provided a curious Leg of Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton for you: <hi>I thank you my Dear,</hi> ſays he, <hi>you are always very free of your Fleſh to me, and every body elſe that has any Appetite to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>151.</label> Some Scholars having a ſpight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Maſter, becauſe of his Harſhneſs to them, reſolv'd to play
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:135151:41"/> him ſome trick; ſo knowing him to be a very curious neat Man, they dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the Rails of the Stairs with a Sr. <hi>R</hi>—Now the Maſter coming down in the dark, laid his Hands in it, which ſet him into a terrible feu'd; ſo he called all the Scholars, and took them into ſtrict Examination; but ſuſpecting one above the reſt, he was very ſharp upon him, urging him to confeſs it, telling him he did it; the Boy utterly denied it; but the Maſter was the more preſſing upon him: <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,</hi> ſaid the Lad, with all the Aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verations imaginable, <hi>I did it not, but if you pleaſe, I'll tell you who had a hand in it:</hi> Hereupon the Maſter thought to have found out the Truth, and ſo very eagerly ask'd him who? <hi>Your Worſhip, Sir,</hi> ſays he: Whereupon he was diſmiſs'd, with the applauſe of all his Fellows, for his Ingenuity.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>152.</label> A Merry Fellow in a great Storm at Sea, when all were at Prayers, Eat heartily on Salt-Beef; and being ask'd his reaſon, anſwer'd, <hi>He ſhould Drink more that day, then ever he did in his life.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:135151:42"/>
               <p>
                  <label>153.</label> 
                  <hi>John Taylor</hi> the Water Poet, being aboard the Ship, call'd, <hi>The Hector,</hi> was ſo Treated with Punch by the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that it was eaſily perceiv'd by the Seamen, who began to play upon him; whereupon <hi>John</hi> in a Poetical rage, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd the Patron of the Ship thus,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Noble <hi>Hector,</hi> Valiant Son of <hi>Priam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Grant all theſe men may be as Drunk as I am.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <label>154.</label> A Certain Knave asking a virtuous Gentlewoman, Jearingly, <hi>What was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty?</hi> She anſwer'd <hi>What's that to you? Meddle with thoſe things that concern you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>155.</label> A Young Man in <hi>London</hi> being caught abed with his Miſtreſs, was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely reprimanded by his Uncle, who ſet before him the example of <hi>Joſeph: Oh,</hi> ſays he, <hi>If Joſeph's Mistreſs had been as handſome as mine, I doubt not but he wou'd have done as I did.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>156.</label> A Gentleman that had many Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, was ſaying one day to his Friend, that his Wife was more Fertile then his Land. <hi>I'll give you a good reaſon
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135151:42"/> for that,</hi> ſays his Friend, <hi>for if you are weary and won't take pains to make her ſo, others will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>157.</label> A Witty Fellow going a long <hi>Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſter-Row</hi> in a dark Winter night, ſaw a Lanthorn hang out with a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in it, which he had a mind to, to light him home; but as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad clim'd up to it, and was juſt goi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to unty it, the Maid of the Houſe ſaw him, and ask'd what he meddled with the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn for? <hi>I beg your Pardon,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Sweet-heart, I only went to ſnuff the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, that I might ſee to go along.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>158.</label> Two Gentlemen riding from <hi>Barnet</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> met a Miller riding ſoftly on his Sacks; and they being merrily diſpos'd, had a mind to abuſe the Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; ſo one went on one ſide of him, and the other on the other, and having Rid ſo a little way with him, they pray'd him to reſolve them one Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Whether,</hi> ſays they, <hi>art thou more Knave or Fool? Truly,</hi> replied the Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, <hi>I don't know which I am moſt, but I think I am between both.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:135151:43"/>
               <p>
                  <label>159.</label> Mr. <hi>Randolph,</hi> the Great Wit of <hi>Cambridg,</hi> coming to <hi>London,</hi> had a mind to ſee <hi>Ben-Johnſon,</hi> who was Drinking at the <hi>Devil-Tavern</hi> with Mr. <hi>Drayton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Daniel,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vester,</hi> three famous Poets of that Age; he being loth to intrude into their Company, and yet deſiring to be call'd in, peep'd in at the door ſeveral times, till at laſt Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> perceiving him, ſaid, Come in, <hi>John Bopeep;</hi> which he did: and when the Reckoning came to be Paid, which was Five Shillings, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey agree'd among themſelves that he that made the beſt <hi>Extempory</hi> Verſes, ſhould be excus'd from paying any thing, and the other four ſhould pay it all, ſo every one made his Verſes, and when it came to Mr. <hi>Randolph</hi>'s turn, he made theſe:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>I <hi>John Bopeep,</hi> to you four Sheep,</l>
                  <l>With each one his good Fleece;</l>
                  <l>If you are willing to pay your five Shilling,</l>
                  <l>'Tis fifteen Pence a piece.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <label>160.</label> 
                  <hi>Ben-Johnſon</hi> and <hi>Silveſter</hi> being very merry one day at the above-nam'd Tavern, began to Rhime upon one another; ſo <hi>Silveſter</hi> began thus:</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:135151:43"/>
                  <l>I <hi>Silveſter</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lay with your Siſter.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>To whom <hi>Ben-Johnſon</hi> anſwer'd:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>I <hi>Ben. Johnſon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lay with your Wife.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>That,</hi> ſays <hi>Silveſter, Is no Rhyme; but, Faith, 'tis true though,</hi> ſays <hi>Ben-John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>161.</label> Mr. <hi>Noy</hi> the Attorney General making a Veniſon Feaſt in a Tavern, where <hi>Ben Johnſon</hi> and ſome of his Companions were Drinking, and he having a mind to ſome of the Veniſon, wrote theſe Verſes, and ſent them to Mr. <hi>Noy:</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>When all the VVorld was drown'd,</l>
                  <l>No Veniſon cou'd be found,</l>
                  <l>For then there was no Park:</l>
                  <l>Lo here we ſit</l>
                  <l>Without e're a bit,</l>
                  <l>Noy <hi>has it all in his Ark.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>For the ingenuity of which, Mr. <hi>Noy</hi> ſent him a good corner of a Paſty, and half a Dozen Bottles of Sack to waſh it down.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>162.</label> At another time, <hi>Ben-Johnſon</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to go through the half-Moon-Tavern
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135151:44"/> in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet,</hi> was deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed entrance, the door being ſhut: up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he made theſe Verſes,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> is ſo unkind, to make me go about,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Sun</hi> my Money now ſhall take the <hi>Moon</hi> ſhall go without.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>And ſo he went to the <hi>Sun-Tavern</hi> at <hi>Long-Lane</hi> end, forſaking the <hi>Half-Moon,</hi> for this affront.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>163.</label> A Fool being very ſick and like to dye, on that went to ſee him, went to comfort him, bidding him chear up, <hi>for if you dye,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Four proper Fellows ſhall carry you to Church: Ay but,</hi> quoth he, <hi>I had rather by half go thither my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>164.</label> A Courtier importuning Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> for a certain place that was vacant, the Queen told him, <hi>He was not fit for it. An't pleaſe your Majeſty,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I can get one to Officiate for me: Very likely,</hi> ſays the Queen, <hi>and I can put in one of my Maids, that can do ſo too.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:135151:44"/>
               <p>
                  <label>165.</label> A Tutor in <hi>Oxford,</hi> reading a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture to his Scholars about the Virtues in moral Philoſophy, gave them this general Rule to know Vertues from Vices, <hi>That Virtues conſiſted in the Middle, but Vices were Extreams.</hi> The next day he bid his Scholars give an Example of the fore-going Rule; ſo one of them, being a ſharp Lad, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanc'd in <hi>Virginity. Why Sirrah,</hi> ſays the Tutor, <hi>who told you that Virginity was a Vertue? You did, Sir,</hi> replied the Lad, <hi>for you told us, that all Virtues conſiſted in the Middle, and ſo does Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>166.</label> Says a Tall Man, going along with a little Man, <hi>The People won't gaze ſo much at a Pigmy, becauſe I'm in your Company. Yes,</hi> ſays the little Man, <hi>they will gaze the more upon me, to ſee me have an Aſs in my Company, and not Ride.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>197.</label> A Lawyer meeting a Countrey Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low driving his Cart, ask'd him mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, why his Fore-ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re was ſo Fat, and the other ſo Lean? <hi>Why,</hi> ſays the Fellow, <hi>my Fore-horſe is a Lawyer,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135151:45"/> and the rest are his Clients;</hi> for which witty anſwer, the Lawyer gave him a Shilling to Drink.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>168.</label> A Countrey-man coming up to <hi>London,</hi> having never been there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſtar'd into a Scriv'ners Shop; the Scriv'ner ſtanding at the Door, ask'd him what he wou'd buy? What do you ſell, ſays the Countrey-man? Why Logger-heads, ſays the Scrivner, will you buy one? <hi>Yes,</hi> ſays he, <hi>but I ſee you have ſuch a good Trade, that you have no Choice, having but one left in your Shop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>169.</label> One ſaid, <hi>That no Man had greater confidence in their Countrey, then Thieves, for they put themſelves upon it, though they are Hang'd for their paims.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>170.</label> One told his Wife, that there was a Law making, That all Cuckolds ſhould be drown'd: <hi>O pray, my Dear Husband,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>then learn to Swim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>171.</label> A Blunt Ruſtical Fellow, having been netled with a Jeſt that one put upon him, reſolv'd one way or other to be even with him; therefore having a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:135151:45"/> good Cane in his Hand, he laid him over the Pate with it ſaying, <hi>Every Man has his Talent; you can break Jests, and I can break Heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>172.</label> Some Thieves coming to Rob a Gentlemans Houſe before he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, he call'd out of the Window, and bid <hi>them ſtay but one hour, and by that time he ſhould be aſleep;</hi> which frighted them ſo, that they ran away faſter then they came thither.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>173.</label> A Gentleman having his Pocket pickt whilſt he was at Prayers at Church, complain'd to his Friend of it; why ſays his Friend, <hi>If you had VVatch'd as well as Pray'd, you would not have loſt your Money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>174.</label> A Conſtable taking a pretty Wench late at Night, brought her before a Juſtice, who ſeeing her handſom and gentilely Dreſt, was very favourable to her, winking at her fault in being out ſo late, and bid the Conſtable take her home to his Houſe that Night. <hi>Yes, that I will with all my heart,</hi> ſays the Conſtable, <hi>if your VVorſhip will be pleas'd to commit my VVife till the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:135151:46"/>
               <p>
                  <label>175.</label> Two young <hi>Oxford</hi> Scholars agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together to go into an Adjacent Warren to ſteal ſome Rabets; one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to watch, and not to ſpeak one word, and the other to catch them: So they being come to the place, he that watch'd, cried out, <hi>Ecce Cuniculi multi;</hi> which noiſe frighted all the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets into their Burrows; whereupon the other was very angry with him; <hi>Why,</hi> ſays he, <hi>who thought that Rabets under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Latin?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>176.</label> A Lady receiving a Letter from a Foppiſh Gentleman, taken <hi>verbatim</hi> out of <hi>Caſſander,</hi> which he had read, ſhe ſent it him back again, bidding the Meſſenger tell him, <hi>That he was miſtaken, for though the Letter was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to her, it was written to Madam</hi> Roxana.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>177.</label> A Gentleman borrowed five Pounds of his Friend, and loſt it at Play; thereupon he ſent to borrow five Pounds more, by the Token that he ow'd him five Pounds already: <hi>Pray,</hi> ſaid his Friend, <hi>bid your Maſter ſend me the Token, and I'll ſend him the five Pounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:135151:46"/>
               <p>
                  <label>178.</label> A Wench that was got with Child, ſent her Friend to the Father of it, to tell him that ſhe was quick; he repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>If ſhe be quick, I'll be as nimble,</hi> and ſo run away.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>179.</label> One ſeeing Doctor <hi>Mathews,</hi> that was a very Learned man, but little of Stature, paſs by, ſaid, <hi>There goes mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Apoſtolorum;</hi> which the Doctor hearing, merrily replied, <hi>That Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew was Maximus Evangeliſtarum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>180.</label> A Gentleman ſtanding in a brown Study, a Lady ask'd him, <hi>What he was thinking of?</hi> He ſaid, <hi>Of nothing: What do you think on,</hi> ſays the Lady, <hi>when you think on nothing? Faith,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Then I think on you, and the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of your Sex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>181.</label> The Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> going the <hi>Northern</hi> Circuit, a Fellow that was try'd for his Robbing, was very importunate with the Judge to be favourable to him, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him that he was a Kin to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: Why, how ſo, ſaid the Judge? Why, anſwer'd the Fellow, <hi>An't pleaſe your Lordſhip, your Name is</hi> Bacon, <hi>and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:135151:47"/> my Name is</hi> Hog, <hi>and thoſe two are alike. 'Tis true,</hi> ſaid the Judge; <hi>but you and I can't be Kindred till you are Hang'd, for</hi> Hog <hi>is never good</hi> Bacon <hi>till 'tis Hang'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>182.</label> King <hi>James</hi> Riding a Hunting in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> comes to a Gate which he muſt go through, and ſeeing a Countrey-Clown at it, he ſays to him, Prethee good Fellow open the Gate? But he knowing who it was, anſwer'd, <hi>No, an't pleaſe your Grace, I am not wortby to be in that Office; but I'll run and fetch Mr.</hi> Johnſon, <hi>who is a Juſtice of Peace, and lives a Mile off, and he ſhall open it for your Grace;</hi> and ſo he run away as faſt as he could, and left the King to open it himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>183.</label> When the Turks were Beſieging <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna,</hi> a Gentleman being to be ſent to the <hi>Grand Vizier,</hi> upon ſome impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Affair, deſir'd to be excus'd; for, ſays he, I'm affraid, becauſe he is ſo faithleſs and treacherous, that he'll take my Head off: <hi>If he does,</hi> ſays the Governour, <hi>I'll take a Thouſand of his Mens Heads off. I, Sir,</hi> replied the Gentleman, <hi>but I queſtion whether any of them will fit my Shoulders.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:135151:47"/>
               <p>
                  <label>184.</label> A young Lad being chid by his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, for lying a Bed ſo long in a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, telling him that ſuch a one had found a Purſe of Money by riſing early in the Morning; <hi>I,</hi> ſays the Lad ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>but he roſe too early that loſt it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>185.</label> A merry Gentleman, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the late Civil Wars, being ask'd, if he ſhould dye, how he would be buried? Anſwered, <hi>With his Face downwards: For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>in a little time</hi> England <hi>will be turn'd up ſide down, and then I ſhall lie right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>186.</label> A man being brought before the Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> for falling down from a Houſe (which he was Tiling) upon a poor man that was going by, and bruiſing him very much: <hi>Look you, Friend,</hi> ſays the Duke to the Man that was hurt, <hi>I'm for the Law of Retaliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; You ſhall go up to the top of the Houſe where he was, and he ſhall go along juſt where you did; and ſo you ſhall fall upon him, and bruiſe him, as much as he did you:</hi> Which unexpected piece of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, put an end to the mans Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:135151:48"/>
               <p>
                  <label>187.</label> A Farmers Daughter in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey bringing up her Fathers Cows near the Houſe to be Milk'd, they all run away from her down a dirty Lane; upon which the Girl cry'd out, <hi>O Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Cows are run down the Lane to the Devil; ſhall I go after them? No, Child,</hi> ſays her Mother, <hi>let your Father go, for he has high Shoon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>188.</label> A Tallow-Chandler having ſome Candles ſtole, complain'd to his Friend: <hi>O,</hi> ſays he, <hi>be patient, for I'm confident in a ſhort Time they'll all come to light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>189.</label> An <hi>Oxford</hi> Scholar coming up to <hi>London,</hi> went into a Houſe of Iniquity in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> which had the <hi>Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-de-luce</hi> to its Sign, where he got a Clap: whereupon he writ theſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes over the door at his going away:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All you that hither chance to come,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mark well e'er you go in;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For Frenchmens Arms are Signs without,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Frenchmens Harms within.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:135151:48"/>
               <p>
                  <label>190.</label> One asking a Painter how he cou'd draw ſuch curious Pictures, and yet get ſuch ugly Children? He anſwer'd, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he drew the Pictures in the day, but got his Children in the night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>191.</label> Another asking why men ſooner gave to Poor People than to Scholars? was anſwer'd, <hi>Becauſe they think they may ſooner come to be Poor, than Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>192.</label> A Player Riding along <hi>Fleetstreet</hi> in great haſte, a Gentleman of the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> ſtop'd him, and ask'd <hi>what Play was to be acted that night?</hi> The Player was not a little vex'd at him, for hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him on ſuch a ſlight occaſion; however recovering himſelf, he told him <hi>he might ſee that on every Poſt: I beg your Pardon,</hi> ſaid the Gentleman, <hi>indeed I took you for a Poſt, you rid ſo faſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>193.</label> Two Gentlemen being drinking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, one of them preſt the other to drink more then he could well bear, and therefore he refus'd it, deſiring to be excus'd; but the other being pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:135151:49"/> well dipt, ſwore he ſhou'd take t'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Glaſs, or elſe he'd run him thro'. <hi>No,</hi> ſays he <hi>you ſhan't, I'll ſave you that labour, for I'll run my ſelf through, and Pledge you afterwards;</hi> ſaying ſo, he run through the door down ſtairs, and left the Spark to pay the Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>194.</label> Sir <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> being ſurveying of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, as he was walking on the Leads of it, there happened to be a Madman there, who ſeeing ſome Jack daws flying about the Church, catch'd up Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> (being a little man) in his Arms, ſaying, <hi>Now Sir, we will fly down as thoſe Birds do;</hi> and ſo was going to throw him over; but he cry'd out to him, ſaying, <hi>Hold Friend, let us go down, and fly up to them,</hi> which ſtopt the Madmans hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>195.</label> A Woman coming to a Parſon, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd him to preach a Funeral Sermon on her Son that was lately dead; the Parſon promiſed her to do it; but ſhe deſiring to know the Price of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, he told her it was Twenty Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: <hi>Twenty Shillings!</hi> ſays ſhe; <hi>An Aſs ſpoke for an Angel, and won't
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135151:49"/> you ſpeak under Twenty Shillings?</hi> The Parſon being a little netled at her, told her ſhe was better Fed then Taught: <hi>Sir,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>'tis very true; for my Huſband feeds me, and You teach me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>196.</label> A Countrey Gentleman riding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> his Horſe ſtumbled and threw him in the Dirt; ſo he got a fellow to hold him, and went into the next Shop; the Miſtreſs of which being a pleaſant Woman, ſmiling, (ſeeing he had no hurt) ask'd him if his Horſe us'd to ſerve him ſo? <hi>Yes Madam,</hi> ſays he, <hi>When he comes juſt againſt a Cuckold's door. Then in truth,</hi> replied ſhe ingeniouſly, <hi>You are like to have twenty falls, before you get to the Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>197.</label> A Gentleman riding to <hi>Epſom,</hi> overtook a hadſome Countrey Wench jogging along eaſily upon a Poor dull Mare; the Gentleman being mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily diſpos'd, ask'd her how ſhe did? and told her, if ſhe pleas'd he'd occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py her. O Sir, ſays ſhe, what good will that do me? Why, ſays he, 'twill make you brave and brisk; <hi>Pray then Sir,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>Occupy my Mare, for ſhe's very dull.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:135151:50"/>
               <p>
                  <label>198.</label> An Elder Brother told his younger Brother, that that White Camlet Cloak he had on, became him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary well: <hi>Faith Brother,</hi> ſays he, <hi>but a black mourning Cloak for you, wou'd become me a great deal better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>199.</label> A Great Swearer being ſubpoena'd to give his Oath upon a Trial, they brought him a Book to ſwear on: <hi>Faith,</hi> ſays he to the Clark, <hi>You may ſave your ſelf that Labour, for there is no Oath but I can Swear it without Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>200.</label> A Scolding Woman us'd to abuſe her husband, who was pretty ſoftly, and call him Cuckold Twenty times a day, which a ſilly Fellow hearing, ſaid, <hi>He wondred the Husband was ſuch a fool to let his Wife know that he was a Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>201.</label> A Drunken Countrey Fellow whoſe name was <hi>Will. Johnſon,</hi> driving his Cart between <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Sturbridg,</hi> fell faſt aſleep in it; and in the mean time his two Horſes were ſtole out of it: he awaking ſaid, <hi>Either I am</hi> Will. Johnſon, <hi>or I am not</hi> Will Johnſon: <hi>if I
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135151:50"/> am</hi> Will. Johnſon, <hi>then I have loſt my two Horſes: if I am not</hi> Will. Johnſon, <hi>then I have found a Cart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>202.</label> A Gentleman diſcourſing of his Travels, was interrupted by a Lady in the Company, that ſaid She had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd further then he: <hi>Say you ſo, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</hi> ſays the Gentleman, <hi>Then We as Travellers, may lye together with Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>203.</label> One that had been married but a Week, call'd her Husband Cuckold: which her Mother hearing, reprov'd her; <hi>You ſlut,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>do you call your Huſband Cuckold already? And I have been married this twenty years to your Father, and never durſt tell him of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>304.</label> A Countrey Man going along <hi>Lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> ſaw a rope with a handle to it hang out of the door; now he not knowing what was the meaning of it, went and play'd with it; and pulling it a little hard, the Merchant being in the Compting-houſe, came out to the door, and ask'd the Countreyman what he wou'd have? He anſwer'd, Nothing but he pull'd the ſtring, and the Bell
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:135151:51"/> rang: the Merchant ſeeing him ſo ſimple, ask'd him what Countrey man he was? I am an <hi>Eſſex</hi>-man, an't pleaſe you, ſays he: <hi>Ay,</hi> ſays the Merchant, <hi>I have heard that in Eſſex a man can't beat the hedg, but out comes a Calf: True,</hi> ſays he, <hi>And I ſee that in London a man can't ring a Bell, but out comes a Cuckold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>205.</label> A Drunken debauch'd Dyer, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining to his Friend that was a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber man, that whatever he took in hand to dye, came to ſome miſchance or other: <hi>O,</hi> ſays his Friend, <hi>The way to ſucceed in your buſineſs, is to amend your Life; for a man that does not live well, can never dye well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>206.</label> A Fidler boaſting what a chaſte Wife he had: ſays a Gentleman, I'll lay my Houſe againſt thy Fiddle, that if I have opportunity, I'll get her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to lie with her: the Wager was laid, and he had the Fidlers conſent to try; but the Fidler went in the mean time, and ſung this Song under the Window:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hold out, my Dear, hold out;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hold out but theſe two houres:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:135151:51"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If you hold out, there is no doubt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But the Houſe and all is ours.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>To which his Wife anſwer'd:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I Faith ſweet William I cannot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He has caught me about the Middle:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He hath me Won, thou art undon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sweet William thou'ſt loſt thy Fiddle.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <label>207.</label> A Facetious Gentleman diſcourſing with a Witty Lady, who was ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Weakneſs of her Sex, and the vaſt advantage that men had above them: <hi>Hold, Madam,</hi> ſaid he; <hi>I beg your Pardon, if I diſſent from you in this commonly-receiv'd-point; for it is no difficult thing to prove that your Sex is now a days ſtronger then ours; for</hi> Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>the ſtrongeſt man, carried only the Gates of the City upon his Shoulders; but now every little Lady of your Sex car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries a Tower upon her Fore-head.</hi> To which ſhe wittily and briskly replied, <hi>Certainly, Sir, you have a very ſtrong Head, to carry ſo many Windmils up and down in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>208.</label> One that had weak Eyes, being jear'd by a man that had clear Eyes; he told him, <hi>They were not ſo dim, but he could
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:135151:52"/> ſee a Fool: It may be ſo,</hi> ſays the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>but you muſt look in a Glaſs then.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>209.</label> A Schoolmaſter examining his Boys, and asking them ſeveral Rules for Pearſing, eſpied one to have a dirty face and hands, and ask'd him by what Rule it was that he was dirty; the Boy readily anſwer'd, <hi>By deme Lavo Lavi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>210.</label> One telling his Friend that he ſaw a Man and his Wife Fighting: Why did not you part 'em, ſays he? <hi>Part 'em!</hi> ſays the Gentleman, <hi>I have been better bred, then to part Man and Wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>211.</label> Some Gentlemen coming into a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern whoſe Sign was the Moon, (where for a Fancy they ſold nothing but Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, for which they were very noted, and had great Cuſtom) call'd for a Bottle of Sack: Whereupon the Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er told him they had none: At which, they not a little admiring, as not knowing the humour, ask'd the Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the reaſon, who told them, <hi>The Man in the Moon drinks Clarret.</hi> The Fancy of which pleas'd them ſo, that they ſaid they were reſolv'd to be
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:135151:52"/> ſociable; and ſo call'd for each Man his Bottle, to drink their Brothers Health in the Moon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>212.</label> One being ask'd what he was that had a fine Wit in Jeſt? Anſwer'd, <hi>A Fool in Earneſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>213.</label> One gave a Fellow a Box o'th' Ear, upon which the Fellow whom he ſtrook gave him another: What do you mean, ſaid he that gave the firſt Box? I did not lend you a Box, I freely gave it you: <hi>No matter,</hi> ſays the other, <hi>I am a Gameſter, and am always us'd to pay the Box.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>214.</label> Says a Gentleman to his Friend, Methinks a Player, has the idleſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of any: <hi>No,</hi> reply'd he, <hi>you are miſtaken, for he is always in Action.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>215.</label> A Gentleman was us'd to ſay of a Drunkard, <hi>That it ſignified not much what he ſaid in his Cups, for he ſeldom ſpake any thing that he could ſtand to, tho made by Indentures.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:135151:53"/>
               <p>
                  <label>216.</label> One ſeeing a Book that was but one ſheet of Paper, ſaid, <hi>A Man need not libel it, for it did Penance in a ſheet already.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>217.</label> One <hi>Tom. Love,</hi> Univerſity Capper in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> ringing in one of the Belfreys, the Clapper of the Bell fell upon his Head, and almoſt kill'd him. An arch young Student ſeeing his Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, and thinking the wound Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, writ over againſt the place where he fell, theſe folloing Verſes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here lies</hi> Tom. Love, <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity Capper;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That liv'd by the Bell, and dy'd by the Clapper.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>But <hi>Tom. Love</hi> recovering, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Verſes, under-writ thus:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tom. Love'<hi>s alive, and lives in hope</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To live by the Bell, when thou dy'ſt by the Rope.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="sayings">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:135151:53"/>
               <head>Witty and Grave SAYINGS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>1.</label> SOuldiers in Peace, are like Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys in Summer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>2.</label> Painters are cunning Fellows, for they have a Colour for whatever they do.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>3.</label> Coblers may be ſaid to be good men, becauſe they ſet men upright, and are always mending Soles.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>4.</label> A Priſon is a good Inſtrument of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, for it makes many Lewd Fellows ſtaid men.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:135151:54"/>
               <p>
                  <label>5.</label> Phyſicians, of all men, have the beſt on't; for if they do well, the World proclaims it; if ill, the Earth covers it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>6.</label> Carpenters are civil and honeſt Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, for they do all their buſineſs by Rule.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>7.</label> Vertue is eaſier than Vice; for the Eſſential difference between Vice and Vertue is Truth and Falſhood, and it is eaſier and leſs pains to tell Truth then a Lye; and for Vices of the Senſes, Cuſtom is all in all; for to one that has liv'd honeſtly, it is as much ſhame to commit Sin, as for another to abſtain.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>8.</label> At a certain Marriage, One let fall this Silver Saying, <hi>That Parents might forbid their Children an unfit Match, but may not force their Conſent to a fit one.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:135151:54"/>
               <p>
                  <label>9.</label> 
                  <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> being accus'd by a Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet for having got her with Child, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, <hi>Thou may'ſt as well, going through a Thorn-Hedge, tell certainly which Thron prick'd thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>10.</label> The Merits of a deſerving Lady are enough to ſerve her for a Protection, amongſt the Savage Indians; whilſt their Rudeneſs and Barbarity knows not ſo perfectly to hate all Vertues, as ſome mens Subtilty does.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>11.</label> Carry a Watchful Eye, upon Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers till they come to ripeneſs; &amp; when they are ripe, let looſe a ſpeedy hand: He that Expects them too long, meets 'em too ſoon, and gives advantage to the Evil. Commit their beginnings to <hi>Argus</hi>'s Eyes, and their End to <hi>Briareus</hi>'s hands, and thou art ſafe.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:135151:55"/>
               <p>
                  <label>12.</label> Fortune has no power over Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but of Senſuality, and of Lives that Swim and Navigate without the Loadſtone of Diſcretion and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>13.</label> 
                  <hi>Ariſtarchus</hi> Scoffingly ſaid, <hi>That in old times hardly cou'd be found ſeven Wiſe Men throughout the World. But in our Days,</hi> ſays he, <hi>much ado there is to find ſo many Fools.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>14.</label> 
                  <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> being ask'd by one, What Learning was moſt neceſſary for Mans Life? Anſwer'd, <hi>To Vnlearn that which is Naught.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>15.</label> 
                  <hi>Diogenes</hi> being ask'd in a kind of ſcorn, What was the Reaſon that Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers haunted Rich Men, and not Rich Men Philoſophers? Anſwer'd, <hi>Becauſe the former knew what they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the latter did not.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:135151:55"/>
               <p>
                  <label>16.</label> When it was ſaid to <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> The Athenians have conde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d you to dye; he ſaid again, <hi>And Nature them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>17.</label> When <hi>Croeſus</hi> for his Glory ſhew'd <hi>Solon</hi> his great Treaſures of Gold, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>If another comes that has better Iron than you, he will be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of all this Gold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>18.</label> 
                  <hi>Chilon</hi> us'd to ſay, <hi>That Gold was try'd with a Touch-ſtone, and Men with Gold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>19.</label> 
                  <hi>Solon</hi> compar'd the People unto the Sea, and the Orators and Counſellors unto the Wind; for that the Sea would be calm and quiet if the Wind did not trouble it.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:135151:56"/>
               <p>
                  <label>20.</label> An Arch Blade us'd to ſay, That of all Trades the Midwives was the moſt commendable: <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>they live not by the hurts of other men, as Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons do; nor by the falling out of Friends, as Lawyers do; but by the Agreement betwixt Party and Party.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bulls">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:135151:56"/>
               <head>Notable BULLS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>1.</label> A Young Countrey Squire riding very hard, his Horſe grew very Sick upon it: he complaining to his Friend; ſays he, <hi>I rid my Horſe hard, and he's ſiek; and I fear he'll never be his own Man again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>2.</label> Another being ask'd whether his Friend <hi>Tom,</hi> that was lately dead, had left him any Legacy? <hi>No Faith,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Not a Teſter to drink his health.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>3.</label> One ask'd a Fellow if he would go into the Water with him: <hi>No,</hi> ſays
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:135151:57"/> he, <hi>I'll never go into the Water till I have learnt to Swim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>4.</label> Some Gentlemen being at Dinner in a Tavern, one of them that was a little nicer then the reſt, ſeeing the Salt look a little dirtily, call'd to the Drawer, <hi>to bring up ſome freſh Salt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>5.</label> Some Gentlemen being at Dinner together, were diverting themſelves with Jeſts and Bulls: One among them more curious then the reſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd an <hi>Oxford</hi> Schollar in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to give him the definition of a Bull; who ingeniouſly told him, <hi>That a Bull was an Ox gelt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>6.</label> A Blind Miniſter coming to ſpeak with a Gentleman, the Gentleman's man came running to him, and told him, <hi>That the Blind Miniſter was come to ſee him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:135151:57"/>
               <p>
                  <label>7.</label> A Young Scholar was very much troubled, and did not like his Dicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onary, Praying his Father to get it chang'd, becauſe, <hi>He could not find what was Latin for</hi> Aqua-vitae <hi>in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>8.</label> A Countrey Juſtice examining a poor thieving Schollar, ſaid, <hi>Sirrah, you are an Arch Rogue, but take warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for if you are once hang'd, your Book can't ſave you from the Gallows.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>9.</label> One being advis'd to go to Sea, <hi>No</hi> ſays he, <hi>I had rather travel all the World over by Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>10.</label> A certain King being ſick, one pray'd, <hi>That he might Reign as long as the Sun and Moon ſhould endure, and the Prince his Son, after him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:135151:58"/>
               <p>
                  <label>11.</label> One finding his Friend abed at Ten a Clock in the Morning, ask'd him why he lay ſo long? <hi>Why Faith,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I came home late laſt night: Why, how late was it,</hi> ſays his Friend? <hi>Late!</hi> ſays he, <hi>'twas three a Clock in the morning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>12.</label> An Ignorant-Fellow complaining of the Folly of the Age, ſaid, <hi>That men were far Wiſer in future times then now.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>13.</label> One boaſting of his Credit, ſaid, <hi>He knew a Scrivener that would lend him Fifty Pounds at any time, on his own Bond, without either Scrip or Scrowl.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>14.</label> One going over in the Ferry-Boat from <hi>Richmond</hi> to <hi>Twitnam,</hi> the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryman's Wife Officiating, admiring ſaid. <hi>He never ſaw a Woman Ferry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:135151:58"/>
               <p>
                  <label>15.</label> Two Perſons going along <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> a Dumb-man accidentally meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'em, joſtled againſt one of them; whereupon he held up his Stick to ſtrike him; but the Dumb-man ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſome ſign, which the Perſon that was with him perceiving, ſtop'd his Friends blow, asking him why he would ſtrike a Dumb-man? <hi>Is he Dumb,</hi> ſays the other? <hi>Why did he not tell me ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>16.</label> One ſpeaking to a Gentleman of the unkindneſs of his ſuppoſed Friend, ſaid, in a Paſſion, <hi>That he had no ſooner turn'd his Back, but the Raſcal abus'd him before his Face.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>17.</label> A Countrey Fellow paſſing by the Exchange, ſaw the Picture of a Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn hang up; ſays he to one that ſtood by, <hi>I have ſeen ſeveral Pictures of theſe Beaſts with one Horn only; pray are not there ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorns with two Horns?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:135151:59"/>
               <p>
                  <label>18.</label> One asking a certain Perſon how his Friend came off at the Seſſions<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe? he told him he was to be Burnt in the Hand; Piſh, ſays the other, that's a ſmall matter; for, <hi>for a little Fee, they'll Burn him in the Hand with a cold Iron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>19.</label> A Sea-Captain was invited to a Hunting-match, who when he came home, related what ſport he had, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner: <hi>Our Horſes,</hi> ſays he, <hi>being well Rigg'd, we man'd them; and the Wind being at Weſt-South-Weſt (Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen of us in Company) away we ſtood o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Downs; in the time of half a Watch, we ſpy'd a Hare under full Gale, we Tackt and ſtood after her, coming up cloſe, ſhe Tackt, and we Tackt, upon which Tack I had like to run aground; but getting clear off, I ſtood after her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but as the Devil would have it, juſt as I was going to lay her aboard, bearing too much Wind, I and my Horſe over-ſet, and came Keel upward.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:135151:59"/>
               <p>
                  <label>20.</label> A ſilly old Fellow meeting his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ask'd him whether he was going? To School, ſaid the Boy: That's well, ſaid he, there's a Penny for you; <hi>Be a good Boy, and mind your Book, and I hope I ſhall live to hear thee Preach my Funeral-Sermon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>21.</label> A fooliſh young Eſquire, being new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to his Eſtate (taking after the old Miſer his Father, grew covetous.) He hearing his Steward ſay, he had kill'd him a Bullock againſt <hi>Chriſtmas. What,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>do you mean to undo me by ſuch extravagant Expences? I will have but half a one kill'd at a time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>22.</label> A Perſon who had not much Wit to ſpare, ſeeing his Son play roguiſh Tricks, <hi>Why Sirrah,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>did you ever ſee me do ſo, when I was a Boy, as you are?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:135151:60"/>
               <p>
                  <label>23.</label> A Preciſe Fellow hearing much Swearing in a Bowling-Green, ſaid, <hi>For ſhame Gentlemen forbear, it is Gods great mercy the Bowling-Green doth not fall on your Heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>24.</label> One ſitting at Supper, his Cat paſt to and fro through his Arms, bruſhing her Tail againſt his Mouth, which made him ſo angry, that he cut off the tip of her Tail, ſaying, <hi>I think now, Miſtriſs Puſs, I have given you an Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark:</hi> For a little time the Cat ſtaid away, but the next day came again, according to her uſual manner; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon in a Rage, ſaid he, <hi>Why, how now, you trouble ſome Bitch? Are you come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? I thought I had given you your Break-faſt laſt night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>25.</label> A Gentleman hiring ſome Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to pull down his old Wall, that he might build a new one; as they
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:135151:60"/> were doing it, cry'd out to them to <hi>have a care, leaſt the Foundation ſhould tumble on their Heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>26.</label> When Guinneys were firſt Coyn'd, they were a great rarity in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: A young Fop coming from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> more Gallant then Wiſe, ſeeing the People ſo earneſt to ſee them, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> ſaid he, throwing down two or three of them on the Table, <hi>Theſe are ſo common in</hi> London, <hi>that you cannot receive Forty Shillings, but you muſt take five or ſix of them whether you will or no.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>27.</label> One going by Water, ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Boat that had affronted him, <hi>Speak another word, and I'll knock your Head and the Wall together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>28.</label> One that was Born in the Pariſh of St. <hi>Giles Cripplegate,</hi> ſaid <hi>When I dye, I'll be Buried in</hi> Cripplegate-<hi>Church-Yard, an't pleaſe GOD I live.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:135151:61"/>
               <p>
                  <label>29.</label> The ſame Perſon affirming there was two ſorts of Fiſhes allow'd to be cry'd on a Sunday; being ask'd what Fiſhes they were, anſwer'd, <hi>Milk and Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaerel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>30.</label> One ſaying, That the Fenny-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys were very unhealthy; <hi>I am of your mind,</hi> ſaid another, <hi>for I liv'd there once; and I believe if I had liv'd there till this time, I had dy'd ſeven Years ago.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="characters">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:135151:61"/>
               <head>Fourteen Ingenious <hi>Characters.</hi> Drawn to the Life.</head>
               <div n="1" type="character">
                  <head>I. <hi>Of a CHARACTER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT gives you the hint of Diſcourſe, but diſcourſes not; and is that in Maſs and Ingot, which you may Coyn and Wyer-draw into infinite; 'tis more <hi>Seneca</hi> than <hi>Cicero,</hi> and ſpeaks rather the Language of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:135151:62"/> 
                     <hi>Oracles</hi> than <hi>Orators:</hi> Every Line's a Sentence, and every two a Period. It ſays not all, but all it ſays is good; and like an Air in Muſick, is either full of Clozes, or ſtill driving towards a Cloſe: 'Tis no long-winded Exerciſe of Spirit, but a forcible one, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſooneſt out of Breath; 'tis all matter, and to the matter; and has nothing of Superfluity, nothing of Circumlocution. So little comporting with Mediocrity, as it extols to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or depreſſes unto Hell; having no mid place for Purgatory left. 'Tis that in every ſort of Writing delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth moſt; and though the Treatiſe be Gold, it is the Jewel ſtill, which the Author of Characters, like your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidary, produces ſingle, whilſt others, Goldſmith like, inchaſe them in their Works. 'Tis a Portraiture not only o'th' Body, but the Soul and Mind: Whence it not only delights, but tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and moves withal, and is a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon as well as Picture to every one. In fine, 'tis a Short Voyage; the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter holds out with equal force, ſtill coming freſh unto his Journeys end, whilſt in long ones they commonly tire and faulter on their way: And to the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:135151:62"/> Reader 'tis a Garden, not a Journey; or a Feaſt, where, by reaſon of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects variety, he is never cloy'd; but at each Character, as at a new Service, falls too with freſh Appetite.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="character">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:135151:63"/>
                  <head>II. <hi>Of an Importunate Dun.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AN <hi>Importunate Dunn,</hi> is the Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of Vexation; a <hi>Single</hi> Plague, worſe then all <hi>Egypts Ten;</hi> a kind of <hi>Subſtantial Ghoſt,</hi> perpetually haunting a man, and ſucking him as eagerly as an <hi>Hobgoblin</hi> does a <hi>Witch;</hi> an <hi>Horſe-leech</hi> that always cries, <hi>Give, give;</hi> or rather a <hi>Cuckow</hi> that has never but one Note, <hi>Pay, Pay, Pay; Money, Money, Money:</hi> A <hi>troubleſome Devil,</hi> not to be <hi>laid</hi> with Holy Water, and only <hi>exorcis'd</hi> by <hi>Silver Croſſes;</hi> an <hi>Evil Spirit,</hi> whom no <hi>Muſick</hi> but the ſweet <hi>Gingling</hi> of Coin can charm.</p>
                  <p>Should we enquire his Pedigree, he ſeems one of <hi>Nimrod's</hi> Baſtards, for he is a Tyrant by Nature, and a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Hunter by Profeſſion. A Blood-Hound of a notable Quick Scent to diſcover his Game, and a deep Mouth to purſue it; he takes upon him a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative to get, where even Kings
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:135151:63"/> themſelves muſt loſe their Rights; Nay, preſumes to Ape <hi>Creation,</hi> by at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to ſqueez <hi>ſomething</hi> out of <hi>nothing,</hi> and raiſe a <hi>World</hi> of Caſh, from the barren Womb of meer <hi>Vacui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He would make an excellent States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for he has the beſt intelligence in the World, and will find out a lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Acquaintance in a City crow'd, or Countrey corner, ſooner then a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> or a limping <hi>Hue and Cry;</hi> Yet nothing lights him to you ſooner, or more exaſperates him againſt you, then a new Suit, a good Dinner, or a merry Glaſs; for he holds it for a Maxime, That whoever owes him any thing, ought to be in Arrear likewiſe both to back and belly. If the Debtor live ſo remote, that he cannot conveniently wait on him every other day, he makes him pay Intereſt (even to Extortion) at the <hi>Post Office;</hi> for he is ſure of more Letters than a <hi>handſome Girl</hi> of ſixteen, that has a great fortune at her own Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; his Stile in theſe <hi>Familiar E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles,</hi> is extreamly civil in the Front, but cloſe and preſſing in the Rear—<hi>He would rather loſe his ſmall concern,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:135151:64"/> than put you to the leaſt inconvenience—But muſt needs have his Money next re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, or elſe ſhall be forced to turn over the Debt, or take his Courſe.</hi> Yet he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes your Non-payment to your unmindfulneſs, and deſires you not to take this one more <hi>Item</hi> unkindly; He talks much in the Language of <hi>Bacon's</hi> Brazen Head, Time's paſt: and (as if you were a ſecond <hi>Joſhuah</hi>) blames you for not keeping the day; he Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends extraordinary kindneſs for you, but hates all Protections ſo much, that he dares not ſay at the end of his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, He commits you to that of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but always hoping to hear from you ſpeedily, and with Effect, reſts, Your humble Servant.</p>
                  <p>At this rate (as the <hi>Weapon-ſalve</hi> heales) he wounds at a diſtance; But if you are come-at-able, (as he calls it) he will rack the very Soul of you; for he attends you as duly as your Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and proves as conſtant a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentor as a Guilty Conſcience to a Murderer: You can neither eat, nor drink, nor ſleep nor walk in quiet for him. Indeed the Tenter-hooks he puts a man upon, are enough to ſtretch the tendereſt Conſcience, and warp the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:135151:64"/> beſt nature in the World; for when he will not be ſatisfied with <hi>Truth,</hi> you are forc'd to tell him what <hi>is not ſo,</hi> to get rid of him; afterwards by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant Importunities, he provokes you to ſwear at him; and at laſt, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, hardens you into a Reſolution, <hi>never to pay him.</hi> Thus we may call him the Devils Uſher, that tempts people from Lying to Swearing, from that to Diſhoneſty, and ſo Improves them from <hi>Form to Form,</hi> in the <hi>School</hi> of wickedneſs, till they are fitted for the <hi>Academy</hi> of Hell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Etymologists</hi> think he is call'd a <hi>Dunn,</hi> by Antiphraſis, becauſe he will never have done bawling; or (as others write) takes the Appellation from a <hi>quondam</hi> famous Officer of Juſtice of that name, with whoſe Nature he ſimpathizes, and worries a poor Man with as little Remorſe, as that <hi>New-gate</hi> Squire could a Traytor. His Faith is enough to make one turn Infidel, for he uſes none ſo bad as thoſe he truſts; Nor can he be counted a Chriſtian, ſince his Charity both begins and ends at home. And it ever he ſays his Prayers, he skips over that Petition, <hi>Forgive us our Debts, as we forgive our
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:135151:65"/> Debtors,</hi> in the <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> as ſlily as a Phanatick does the Article of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in the Catholick Church,</hi> in the <hi>Creed.</hi> He is commonly early up, and never the near; for he wakes a man in a morning, before the <hi>Lark</hi> is up to chaunt her Mattins, and a Guard of <hi>Switzers</hi> cannot keep him out of ones Chamber; alledging Buſineſs, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, ſleep or ſickneſs, cannot divert his perſecutions: And 'tis happy for him that doors can't maintain Actions of <hi>Aſſault</hi> and <hi>Battery.</hi> He beats up your Quarters ſo often, that they quickly learn to <hi>deny you</hi> at home; but if he chance to find you at any of your Haunts, he makes you believe 'twas by the meereſt Accident, though he have waited <hi>eight and forty</hi> hours on purpoſe. However he is <hi>heartily glad to ſee you,</hi> (that's the only Truth you ſhall have of him) and ſhaking you by the hand, he asks you,—<hi>What News?</hi> But before you can anſwer, out comes the <hi>little money between us.</hi> Then, Lord bleſs him! <hi>Times are ſo hard, and money was never ſo ſcarce ſince</hi> Adam <hi>wore Fig-leav'd Breeches!</hi> His Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors <hi>are ſo urgent, they won't be put off, but he muſt forthwith make up a Sum,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:135151:65"/> and therefore if you cannot help him to all,</hi> ſpare him but a little, for five pound now will do him as much good, as fifty another time; Nay, 'twil be as great a favour, as if you gave it him out of your Purſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With this rally of Rhetorick, the bluſhing Debtor is Non-pluſt, and Promiſes as many impoſſibilities, as a <hi>Quack Doctor,</hi> or a trembling <hi>Cully,</hi> under the Terrors of a <hi>Bully Rampant;</hi> only ſilently wiſhes, he had a handful of <hi>Guinnies</hi> to beat out his brains with; for he is as much afraid of him, as a <hi>ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy Prentice</hi> of meeting a Gentleman at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> whom he hath affronted in the City; This makes him ſhun the place where he lives, as bad as a Peſt houſe; And (if we may credit an experienc'd Author) when he is to paſs from <hi>Algat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> to <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> and the low ebb in his Pocket will not ſuffer him to go by Water, he muſt firſt trot down to <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> thence ſtrike up to <hi>Norton-Falgate,</hi> then down again to <hi>Queen-hive,</hi> thence up to <hi>Charter-houſe-Yard,</hi> from thence to <hi>Salisbury</hi> Court, and ſo to <hi>Red-Lyon-Fields,</hi> before he can reach <hi>Drury-Lane</hi> in Safety; and yet for all this
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:135151:66"/> caution, his head ſtands awry, with continual looking about.</p>
                  <p>Yet take them both together, they are two of the greateſt Hypocrites in Nature; for though behind one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Backs they rail each at other, as bad as a Weaver againſt a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> yet when they meet, they are ſo <hi>glad to ſee one another! And truly, I have ever found you very Civil to me,</hi> ſays one, <hi>and I can't in the least queſtion your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty,</hi> ſays the other; when the ſhort of it is, 'tis forty to one, but one of them will prove a rank Knave; The Creditor, if ever he be paid; or the Debtor, if he never pay.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="character">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:135151:66"/>
                  <head>III. <hi>Of a Serjeant, or Baylif, and his Setting-Cur.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe firſt, is a kind of Excreſcence of the Law, like our Nails, made only to Scratch and Claw; A ſort of Bird-lime, where he lays hold, he hangs; a Raven that picks not out mens Eyes, as others do, but all his ſpight is at their Shoulders; and you had better have the Night-Mare ride you, then this Incubus. He is one of <hi>Deucalion's</hi> By-blows, begotten of a Stone, and has taken an Oath never to pitty <hi>Widow nor Orphan.</hi> His firſt bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is to bait you for money for his (confounded) civility; next to call for Drink as faſt as men for Buckets of Water in a Conflagration; After which, becoming grave and ſerious, he adviſes you in revenge to Arreſt the Plantiff, and offers to do it; with or without cauſe; 'tis all one to him, if he perceive you have money.</p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:135151:67"/>
                  <p>His Follower is an Hanger that he wears by his ſide; a falſe Dye of the ſame Ball, but not the ſame Cut, for it runs ſomewhat higher, inflames the Reckoning, and ſo does more miſchief. He's a Tumbler that drives in all the Coneys; but is yet but a bungler, and knows not how to cut up a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tearing, unleſs by a pattern. This is the Hook that hangs under water to choak the Fiſh, and his Officer the Quill above, which pops down as ſoon as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Bait is ſwallowed. Though differing in degree, they are both much of a complexion, only the Teeth of this latter are more ſharp, and he more hungry, becauſe he does but ſnap, and hath not his full half ſhare of the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. A main part of his Office is to ſwear and bluſter at their trembling Priſoners, and cry, <hi>Confound us! Why do we wait? Let's Shop him:</hi> Whilſt the other replies, <hi>Jack be patient, 'tis a civil Gentleman, and I know will conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us:</hi> Which ſpecies of wheedling in Terms of their Art, is called, <hi>Sweeten and Pinch.</hi> The Eyes of theſe Wolves are as quick in their Heads, as a <hi>Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purſes</hi> in a Throng; and as nimble are they at their buſineſs, as an <hi>Hang-man</hi>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:135151:67"/> at an Execution. They'll court a <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Pate,</hi> to heal it with a Plaiſter of <hi>Green-wax,</hi> and ſuck more Silver out of a Wound, than a Chyrurgeon. Yet as theſe Eels are generally bred out of the mud of a Bankrupt, ſo they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly dye with their Guts ript up, or are decently run through the Lungs; and as they liv'd hated, die unpitied. We ſpeak here of thoſe only that abuſe the intentions of the Law, and act Oppreſſion under the Colour of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving common Juſtice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="character">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:135151:68"/>
                  <head>IV. <hi>Of a Paun-Broker.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AN Unconſcionable Paun-Broker, (for there are conſcionable Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in that way, that are a Relief and Comfort to the Poor, and thoſe are not concern'd in this Character;) An unconſcionable Paun-broker, I ſay, is <hi>Pluto</hi>'s Factor, Old <hi>Nick</hi>'s Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe-keeper, an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Jew, that lives and grows fat on Fraud and Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Toads on filth and venom; whoſe Practice outvies <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> as much as <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt</hi> ſimple Fornication; and to call him a <hi>Tradeſman,</hi> muſt be by the ſame Figure that Pickpockets ſtile their Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerdemain an <hi>Art and Myſtery.</hi> His Shop like Hell-Gates, is always open, where he ſits at the Receipt of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, like <hi>Cacas</hi> in his Den, ready to devour all that is brought him; and having gotten your <hi>Spoils,</hi> hangs them up in <hi>Rank</hi> and <hi>File,</hi> as ſo many Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies of Victory: Hither all ſorts of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:135151:68"/> Garments reſort in Pilgrimage, whilſt he playing the <hi>Pimp,</hi> lodges the <hi>Tab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Petticoat</hi> and <hi>Ruſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t Breeches</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the <hi>ſame Bed</hi> of Lavender. He is the Treaſurer of the Thieves <hi>Exchequer,</hi> the common Fender of all <hi>Bulkers</hi> and <hi>Shop-lifts</hi> in the Town. To this purpoſe he keeps a private Warehouſe, and Ships away the Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Goods by wholeſale; dreading nothing ſo much, as that a Convict ſhould honeſtly confeſs how he diſpos'd the Moveables: He is a kind of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe quite contrary to the <hi>Gout;</hi> for as that haunts the Rich, ſo this mainly torments the Poor, and ſcarce leaves them ſo much as a primitive Figleaf to cover their Nakedneſs. Mris <hi>Jone,</hi> when ſhe is minded to ſee her ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heart, and Gammer <hi>Blew-bottle</hi> going to a Chriſtening, muſter up the Pence o'th' Saturday Night, to redeem their beſt Rigging out of Captivity; but on Monday Morning infallibly bring them back (like Thieves that had only made an eſcape) to the old <hi>Limbus;</hi> and this ſo often, till at laſt they know the way, and can go to Pawn alone by themſelves. Thus they are forc'd to purchaſe the ſame Cloaths ſeven times
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:135151:69"/> ever; and for want of a Cheſt to keep them in at home, it coſts thrice as much as they are worth for their Lodging in his cuſtody. When they come in, like other Priſoners, they firſt pay Garniſh, the Two pence for Entrance money; after this, Six-pence a Month for every Twenty Shillings lent, (which yet indeed is but 19 s 6d.) that is (according to their Reckoning of thirteen Months to the Year) Six Shillings and Six-pence Intereſt for one Pound for a Year; which makes Thirty three Pounds, Six Shillings and Eight-pence in the hundred, <hi>viz.</hi> one third part of the Principle, and juſt 27l. 6s. 8d. more then the Statute allows; beſides Twelve-pence for a Bill of Sale, if the matter be confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. So that ſince they never lend half the value on any thing that is brought them; if a Pawn-Broker lay out an Hundred Pounds, he firſt makes near Forty <hi>per Annum</hi> Advantage cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as aforefaid: And then conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how many Thieves, &amp;c. (their chiefeſt Cuſtomers that bring the lumping Bargains) never intend to redeem, and how many Poor are not able (eſpecially ſince as ſoon as the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:135151:69"/> Year and Day expire, they preſently diſpoſe their Pawns, or pretend to do ſo) we may reaſonably conclude, that theſe Horſe-Leeches make <hi>Cent per Cent</hi> at leaſt of their money in the Year: And all this by a courſe tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only to the encouragement of Thieves, and Ruine of thoſe that are Honeſt, but Indigent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="character">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:135151:70"/>
                  <head>V. <hi>Of a PRISON.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Priſon is the Grave of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, where they are ſhut up from the World and their Friends; and the Worms that Gnaw upon them, are their own Thoughts and the Jaylor. 'Tis a Houſe of Meagre looks, and ill ſmells, for Lice, Drink and Tobacco, are the Compound; <hi>Pluto's</hi> Court was expreſt from this fancy. And the Perſons are much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame Party that is there. You may ask as <hi>Manippus</hi> in <hi>Lucan,</hi> which is <hi>Nireus?</hi> which <hi>Therſities?</hi> which the Beggar? which the Knight? For they are all ſuited in the ſame form of a kind of Naſty Poverty; only to be out at Elbows is in faſhion here, and 'tis a great Indecorum not to be Thread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare. Every Man ſhews here like ſo many Wrecks upon the Sea, here the Ribs of a Thouſand Pounds, and here the Relick of ſo many Mannours,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:135151:70"/> is a Doublet without Buttons; and 'tis a ſpectacle of more pity then Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions are. The Company one with another is but a vying of complaints, and the cauſes they have to rail on Fortune, and fool themſelves; and there is a great deal of good fellowſhip in this. They are commonly, next their Creditors, moſt bitter againſt the Lawyers, as Men that have had a great ſtroke in aſſigning them thither. Mirth here is ſtupidity or hard heart edneſs, yet they feign it ſometimes, to ſhun Melancholy, and keep off them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from themſelves, and the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thinking what they have been. Men huddle up their life here as a thing of no uſe, and wear it out like an old Suit, the faſter the better; and he that deceives the Time beſt, beſt ſpends it. It is the place where new commers are moſt welcomed, and next them ill News, as that which extends their Fellowſhip in Miſery, and leaves few to inſult; and they breathe their diſcontents more ſecurely here, and have their Tongues at more liberty then their Bodies. Men ſee here much Sin and Calamity, and when the laſt does not mortifie, the other hardens;
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:135151:71"/> and thoſe that are wicked here, are deſperately wicked, as thoſe from whom the horrour of Sin is taken off, and the puniſhment Familiar. And commonly a hard thought paſſes on all that come from this School: Which though it teach much Wiſdom, it is too late, and with danger: And it is better to be a Fool, then to come here to learn it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="character">
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:135151:71"/>
                  <head>VI. <hi>Of a TAVERN.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Tavern is a degree, or (if you will) a pair of Stairs above an Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, where men are Drunk with more Credit. If the Vintners Noſe be at the door, it is a Sign ſufficient, but the abſence of this is ſupply'd by a Buſh: The Rooms are ill breathed, like the Drunkards that have been well waſh't over Night, and are ſmelt to faſting next morning, not furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Beds apt to be deſiled, but more neceſſary Implements, Chairs, Tables, and a Chamber-pot. It is a broacher of more News then Hogs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, and more Jeſts then News; which are ſuckt up here by ſome ſpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy Brain, and from thence ſqueez'd into a Comedy. Men come here to make merry, but indeed make a Noiſe, and this Muſick above, is anſwer'd with the Chatting below: The Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:135151:72"/> are the chiefeſt People in it: Men of <hi>good bringing up;</hi> and howſoever we eſteem of them, none can boaſt more juſtly of their <hi>High Calling.</hi> It is the beſt Theater of Natures, where they are truly acted, not plaid; and the buſineſs, as in the reſt of the World, up and down; that is, from the bottom of the Cellar to the Great Chamber. A Melancholy man would find matter to work upon, to ſee Heads as brittle as Glaſſes, and as often bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Men come hither to quarrel, and come hither to be made friends. It is the common Conſumption of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, and the Murderer or Maker away of a Rainy day. It is the <hi>Torrid Zone</hi> that ſcorches the Face, and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco the Gun-powder that blows it up. A Houſe of Sin you may call it, but not a Houſe of Darkneſs, for the Candles are never out; and it is like thoſe Countries far in the North, where it is as clear at Mid-night as at Mid-day. After a long ſitting, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes like a ſtreet in a daſhing ſhower, where the Spouts are fluſhing above, and the Conduits running below: while the Jordans, like ſwelling Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, overflow their Banks. To give the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:135151:72"/> total reckoning of it, 'Tis the Buſie mans Recreation, the Idle mans Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Melancholy mans Sanctuary, the Inns-a-Court-mans Entertainment, the Schollars Kindneſs, and the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens Courteſie. It is the Study of Spark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Witts, and a Cup of Canary their Book, where we leave them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="character">
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:135151:73"/>
                  <head>VII. <hi>Of a SCOLD.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Rank Scold is a Devil of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Gender; a <hi>Serpent</hi> perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually a hiſſing and ſpitting of Venom; a Compoſition of <hi>Ill-nature</hi> and <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</hi> You may call her animated <hi>Gun-Powder,</hi> a walking Mount-<hi>Aetna,</hi> that is always belching forth flames of Sulphur. A Burr about the Moon, is not half ſo certain a preſage of a <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt</hi> at Sea, as her Brow is of a <hi>Storm</hi> on Land. And though <hi>Laurel, Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn,</hi> and <hi>Seal-Skin</hi> are held preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatives againſt Thunder, Magick has not been able to find out any Amulet ſo ſoveraign as to ſtill her Ragings; for like Oyl pour'd on fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mes, good words do but make her rage the faſter; and when once her Flag of Defiance, the Tippet, is unfurl'd, ſhe cares not a ſtraw for Conſtable nor Cucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool.</p>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:135151:73"/>
                  <p>Her Tongue is the Clapper of the Devils Saints-Bell, that rings all-in to confuſion. It runs round like a Wheel, one Spoke after another, and makes more Noiſe and Jangling, than Countrey-ſteeples on the Fifth of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If ſhe be of the preciſer caſt, ſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes Sacred-Language in her Railing, as Conjurers do in their Charms; calls her Neighbours <hi>Heathen Edomites,</hi> her Husband <hi>Reprobate,</hi> or Son of <hi>Belial;</hi> and will not Cudgel her Maid without a Text for't. But now I ſpeak of Husband, methinks I ſee the <hi>Creeping Snail,</hi> ſhivering in an Ague fit when he comes in her preſence. She is worſe then Cow-itch in his Bed, and as good as a Chafing-diſh at Board; But has either quite forgot his Name, or elſe ſhe likes it not; which makes her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptize him with more noble Titles, as, <hi>White-liver'd Raskal, Drunken Sot, Sneaking Nickompoop,</hi> or <hi>Pittiful Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey Tom Farthing.</hi> Thus ſhe worries him out of his Sences at home, and then ſhe ferrets his Haunts abroad worſe than a Needy Bawd does a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay'd Bully's. In a word, <hi>A Virulent Scold</hi> is her Neighbours perpetual Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:135151:74"/> her Families Evil Genius, her Husbands Ruine, and her own daily Tormentor: And that you may the better knw her Pedigree, I'll give you a ſerious Account of the Receipt or Method made uſe of for her Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the World, lately found in a long-concealed Manuſcript of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus Bombastas Paracelſus;</hi> as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nature to form a <hi>Scold,</hi> firſt took of the Tongues and Galls of <hi>Bulls, Bears, Wolves, Magpies, Parrots, Cuckows,</hi> and <hi>Nightingals,</hi> of each a like num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: The Tongues and Tails of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Adders, Snakes</hi> and <hi>Lizards,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a piece: <hi>Aurum Fulminans, Aqua-Fortis</hi> and <hi>Gun-Powder,</hi> of each one Pound: The <hi>Clappers</hi> of Nineteen <hi>Bells,</hi> and the <hi>Peſtles</hi> of a dozen <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries Mortars.</hi> Which being all mixt, ſhe Calcin'd in Mount <hi>Strom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bello,</hi> and diſſolv'd the Aſhes in a Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſtill'd juſt under <hi>London</hi>-Bridge at three quarters Flood, and Filtrated it through the Leaves of <hi>Calapines</hi> Dictionary, to render the Operation more Verbal. After which, ſhe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd it again through a <hi>Speaking-Trumpet,</hi> and clos'd up the remaining
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:135151:74"/> Spirits in the Mouth of a Cannon. Then ſhe open'd the Graves of all new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceaſed <hi>Pettifoggers, Mountebanks, Barbers, Coffee-News-Mongers,</hi> and <hi>Fiſh-Wives;</hi> and with the Skins of their Tongues made a Bladder, cover'd o'er with <hi>Drum-heads,</hi> and fill'd with <hi>Storms, Tempeſts, Whirl-winds, Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Lightnings, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Incorporation, ſhe ſet ſeven years in a <hi>Rough Sea</hi> to Ferment, and then mixing them with the reſt, rectified the whole three times a day for a Twelve month in a Balnea of Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver. Laſtly, to Irradiate the whole El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xir, and make it more Churliſh, ſhe cut a Vein under the Tongue of the <hi>Dog-ſtar,</hi> drawing thence a Pound of the moſt cholerick Blood; from which Sublimating the Spirits, ſhe mixt them with the Foam of a Mad-Dog; and then putting all together in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Bladder, ſtitcht it up with the Nerves of <hi>Socrates</hi>'s Wife. Out of this notable Preparatory, Dame Nature compos'd a <hi>Shrew.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="character">
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:135151:75"/>
                  <head>VIII. <hi>Of a BAD HUSBAND.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Bad Husband, is an inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate piece of Sottiſh Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance. For though he conſiſts of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ill Ingredients, yet ſtill good Fellowſhip, is the <hi>Cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> and gives him the <hi>Ho-go.</hi> He is the Wiſe Mans Scorn, the Shirks Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and the wheedling Hoſteſſes Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Man; The Moth of an Eſtate, the Shipwrack of a Family, or a miſchief Three-ſtory-high; for he ſcandalizes his Anceſtors, ruines himſelf, and ſtrangles the hopes of all his Poſterity. He throws away his Wealth as heartily as young Heirs, or old Philoſophers and is ſo eager of a Goal, or a Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers Wallet, that he will not wait Fortunes leiſure to undoe him, but Rides Poſt to <hi>Beggers-Buſh;</hi> and takes more pains to ſpend money, then Day-Labourers
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:135151:75"/> to get it; whilſt ſtill his word is, <hi>Let's not pinch while we have it, ſince 'tis time enough to want when we have it not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He knows no difference between Prodigality and Liberality, but is ſo ſooliſhly free, that he dries up the Springs of Bounty, by cutting down the Banks, and letting the Streams run at waſte. If he pretends to Gentility, he thinks he can no way make good that Title, but by paying (where ever he comes) all the whole Reckoning; and every Raſcal that can but cry, <hi>My Noble Maſter,</hi> is Maſter of his whole Purſe; which ſucking Vermine conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually nutter about him, as thick as Flies in a Confectioners-ſhop. If he go to Market, 'tis but to purchaſe a Fox, and two days after returns, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only Truckt away his Corn for Drink, and put off his Cattle to make him a greater Beaſt.</p>
                  <p>His firſt buſineſs after Marriage, is to pay Ale houſe Scores with his Wives Portion; and his next, to Pawn her Cloths for ſupplies of freſh Debauchery. If he be a Citizen, he counts his Shop a Priſon, till at laſt he is Shop'd in a Priſon indeed. He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:135151:76"/> always extraordinary buſineſs abroad, and muſt needs go to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change; when he has nothing to do there, <hi>But change Shillings into Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, and reduce Guinneys into Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things.</hi> He ſtill cries, <hi>'Tis too ſoon to go home yet; and will trudge a Mile about, rather then come near his own Door, for fear he ſhould be oblig'd to come in before his hour, which is mid-night, or paſt;</hi> for if he goes home before, he ſays, <hi>He can never ſleep well.</hi> He is an Hogſhead ſet up upon two ſtumps, fit for nothing but to hold ſtrong Drink; and if he be not at the Pot, is like a Fiſh out of Water, that does nothing but Gape. He thinks Nature gave him <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> not ſo much to Speak, as to take off his Liquor; and his only enquiry is, <hi>Where dwells the beſt Sack and Claret?</hi> He is a paſſionate lover of Morning-Draughts, which he generally continues till Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-time; a rigid exacter of <hi>Num-Groats,</hi> and Collector-General for <hi>Foys</hi> and <hi>Riberidg:</hi> He admires the Prudence of that Apothegm, <hi>Let's drink firſt;</hi> and would rather fell 20 <hi>per Cent</hi> to loſs, than make a dry Bargain. You ſhall infallibly find him and his Tribe about the Fag-end of the day at Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvouz,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:135151:76"/> like a Conſtellation fix'd in the lower Region of a known Tavern, where their Noſes appear like Comets, that evermore portend exceſſive Droughts: They go in upon Parol not to exceed <hi>Three-pences,</hi> but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come out under a <hi>Half-Crown Club:</hi> and their Noiſe (for Diſcourſe you cannot call it) is more Nonſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Impertinent than a She Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Sermon, or the Tattles of an Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitting. As ſoon as they are accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated with a private Room, an half Pint (for ſo they modeſtly begin) ſome clean Pipes, and a Jordan; their firſt Argument is the goodneſs of the Wine, which being voted a Flower, produces next a Bottle; and then News is the Subject of debate; or for want of that, who was moſt Drunk the night before, or Reel'd home with the greateſt Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and Decorum. Though they live like Publicans, yet they imitate Phariſees in their exactneſs of making clean the inſide of the Glaſs; and their ſtricteſt Criticiſms are, <hi>See it go round, and take it off, Sir.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this ſweet Society, our truſty <hi>Troj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> bears his part, till he has not diſcretio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> enough left to know at which
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:135151:77"/> end to light his Pipe; then ſtaggering away (if he eſcape the <hi>Compter</hi>) 'tis forty to one, but he meets with ſome little <hi>Town. Baggage,</hi> who picks his Pocket, and in Requital, beſtows up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him a ſwinging <hi>Clap.</hi> In the mean time the good Woman at home ſits lamenting till Twelve at night, over a piece of mouldy Bread, and a draught of Rot-gut; and the Children are fain, to go to Bed without their Supper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the vile Milk-woman is grown faithleſs: At laſt, when her precious Husband comes with a Breath that ſtinks with Canary and Tobacco, worſe then Hell of Brimſtone; he perhaps picks a cauſe-leſs quarrel, gives her a remembrance with a Bed-ſtaff, that ſhe is forc'd to wear the <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Arms a week after; which the good natur'd Soul muſt excuſe, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending an unlucky Fall, or blaming an innocent Door-latch for the Injury. But put caſe he go peaceably to Bed, what comfort can be expected from ſuch a <hi>Swine?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="character">
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:135151:77"/>
                  <head>IX. <hi>Of a TOWN-FOP.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Town-Fop</hi> is one that plays <hi>Rex</hi> where ever he comes, and makes as much hurry as <hi>Robin. good-Fellow</hi> of old, amongſt our <hi>Granams Milk-bowls;</hi> he is a kind of a <hi>Squib</hi> on a <hi>Rope, a Meteor</hi> compos'd of <hi>Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit</hi> and <hi>Noiſe,</hi> that by <hi>blazing</hi> and <hi>cracking</hi> engages the wonder of the Ignorant, till on a ſudden he vaniſhes and leaves a <hi>ſtench,</hi> if not <hi>infection</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him; he is too often the <hi>ſtain</hi> of a good Family, and by his <hi>Debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed life</hi> blots the noble <hi>Coat</hi> of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors: A wild unback'd Colt, whoſe <hi>Brains</hi> are not half <hi>codled;</hi> indebted for his Cloaths to his Taylor, and for his Wit, (ſuch as it is) to his Company. The School had no ſooner indued him with a few Superficial beſprinklings, but his Mothers Indulgence poſted him to Town for genteeler breeding, where
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:135151:78"/> three or four wild Companions, half a dozen bottles of Burgundy, two leaves of <hi>Leviathan,</hi> a brisk encounter with his Landlords Glaſs-windows, the charms of a little <hi>Miſs,</hi> and the ſight of a new Play, dub'd him at once both a Wit and a Hero; ever ſince he va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues himſelf mainly for underſtanding the <hi>Town,</hi> and indeed knows moſt things in it that are not worth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: The two Poles wherein all his diſcourſes turn, are <hi>Athciſm</hi> and <hi>Baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry,</hi> bar him from being prophane and obſcene, and you cramp his Ingenuity, which forthwith flags and becomes uſeleſs, as a meere common Lawyer, when he has croſs'd the Channel.</p>
                  <p>He is ſo refractory to Divinity, that Morallity it ſelf cannot hold him: He affirms humane Nature knows no ſuch things as Principles of good or evil; and will ſwear, <hi>all Women are Whores,</hi> though his Mother and Siſter ſtand by; whatſoever is Sacred or Serious, he ſeeks to render ridiculous, and thinks Government and Religion fit objects for his idle and fantaſtick Buffoonry; His humour is proud and aſſuming as if he would Palliate his ignorance by ſcoffing at what he underſtands not
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:135151:78"/> and therefore with a pert and pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſcorn, deprecates all things of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler moment, but moſt paſſionately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects pretty All a-mode words, and is as covetous of a new Song or Ayr, as an Antiquary of <hi>Cato's Statue,</hi> with never an Arm and but half a Noſe; theſe keep him always imploy'd, and fill up the <hi>Groteſco's</hi> of his Converſation, whilſt with a ſtately Galantry, once in every half hour he Combs out his <hi>Wig,</hi> Carreens his <hi>Breches,</hi> and new Marinals his <hi>Garniture,</hi> to the Tune of, <hi>Methinks the poor Town has been troubled too long.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>His mind uſed to whiſtle up and down in the levities of Fancy, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminated by the childiſh <hi>Toying</hi> of a rampant imagination, finds it ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed for all ſolid imployment, eſpecially the ſerious exerciſes of <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> which begets an Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to thoſe lovely Beauties, and that prompts him on all occaſions to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them as ridiculous and vain: Hence by degrees he comes to a buſe <hi>Sacred Scripture,</hi> makes a mock of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Flames,</hi> joques on the venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble myſteries of Religion; and in fine, ſcoffs at that All Glorious and Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:135151:79"/> Majeſty, before whom his Brother Wits below tremble. 'Tis true, He will not confeſs himſelf <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> yet in his heart the Fool hath ſaid it, and boaſts aloud, that he holds his Goſpel from the Apoſtle of <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> though it is more then probable he ne're read, at leaſt underſtood, Ten leaves of that unlucky Author. Talk of Witches and you tickle him; ſpeak of Spirits, and he tells you he knows none better then thoſe of Wine; name but Immaterial Eſſence, and he ſhall flout at you as a dull Fop, incapable of Senſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for Converſation; Nor is he better pleas'd, then when he can here hedge in ſome raw Divine, to Bull-bait with Scurrility and all kind of Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <p>By means of ſome ſmall ſcraps of <hi>Learning,</hi> matcht with a far greater ſtock of <hi>Confidence,</hi> a voluble <hi>Tongue,</hi> and a bold <hi>Delivery,</hi> he has the ill luck to be celebrated by the Vulgar, for a man of parts; which Opinion gains credit to his Inſolences, and ſets him on further Extravagances to maintain his Title of Wit, by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing his practice of Fooling; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, all his mighty parts are ſum'd up
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:135151:79"/> in this inventory: <hi>Imprimis, A Ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling way of</hi> Fancy, <hi>a lucky hit at</hi> Quib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>now and then an odd</hi> Metaphor, <hi>a conceited</hi> Irony, <hi>a ridiculous</hi> Simile, <hi>a wild</hi> Fetch, <hi>an unexpected</hi> Inference, <hi>a</hi> Mimick-Geſture, <hi>a pleaſing</hi> knack <hi>in humouring a</hi> Tale; and laſtly, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n irreſiſtable Reſolution of ſpeaking</hi> laſt, <hi>and never be</hi> daſht <hi>out of</hi> Countenance.</p>
                  <p>By theſe Arts, dexterouſly manag'd, he engroſſes a vaſt Repute: The grave Citizens call him ſhrew'd man, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Head-piece; the Ladies (we mean the things ſo call'd of his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) vote him a moſt accompliſht Gentleman, and the Blades ſwear he is a walking Comedy, the only <hi>Merry Andrew</hi> in the Age, that ſcatters Wit where ever he comes, as beggars do Lice, or <hi>Musk-cats</hi> Perfumes; and that nothing in Nature can compare with him.</p>
                  <p>You would think he had gotten the <hi>Lullian</hi> Art, for he ſpeaks <hi>Extempore</hi> on all Subjects, and ventures his words without the relief of Sence to ſecond them; his thoughts ſtart from his Imagination, and he never troubles himſelf to examine their decency, or ſolidity by <hi>Judgment;</hi> to diſcourſe
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:135151:80"/> him ſeriouſly, is to read the <hi>Ethicks</hi> to a <hi>Monkey,</hi> or make an Oration to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula's Horſe,</hi> whence you can only expect a <hi>Wee-hee</hi> or <hi>Jadiſh ſpurn;</hi> after the moſt convincing arguments, if he can but muſter up one plauſible Joque, you are routed. For he that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not your Logick, apprehends his Droll; and though <hi>Syllogiſms</hi> may be anſwer'd, yet <hi>Jeſts</hi> and loud <hi>Laughter</hi> can never be confuted, but have more ſway to degrade things with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking <hi>Croud,</hi> theu <hi>Demonſtrations;</hi> there being a Root of envy in too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men, that invites them to applau'd that which expoſes and villifies what they cannot comprehend. He pretends great skill in curing the <hi>Tetters</hi> and <hi>Ring-worms</hi> of State, but blows in the ſores till they rankle with his poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Breath; he ſhoots <hi>Libels</hi> with his forked <hi>Tongue</hi> at his Superiours, and abuſes his deareſt <hi>Friends,</hi> chuſing to forfeit his Neck to the <hi>Gibbet,</hi> or his Shoulders to the <hi>Battoon,</hi> rather then loſe the drieſt of his idle <hi>Quibbles.</hi> In brief, He is the <hi>Jack-Pudding</hi> of <hi>Socity,</hi> a <hi>Fleering Buffoon;</hi> a better kind of <hi>Ape,</hi> in the Judgment of all <hi>wiſe men;</hi> but an incomparable <hi>Wit,</hi> in his <hi>own.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="character">
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:135151:80"/>
                  <head>X. <hi>Of a Fantaſtique Lady.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HEr Life is a perpetual Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, ſhe would, and ſhe would not; and, <hi>Make ready the Coach, yet let it alone too; Drive to ſuch a place, yet do not neither,</hi> is her ordinary Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: She differs from the <hi>Irreſolute,</hi> in that he is always beginning, and ſhe never makes an end: She writes and blots out again, whilſt he deliberates what to write; th'one being a Reſty, and the other a Reſtleſs Pain: So you can tell what to make of t'one's Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, and how two Negatives make an Affirmative; but of her 'I and No together, you know not what to make, but only that ſhe knows not what to make of it her ſelf. Her Head is juſt like a Mill, or Squirrels Cage, and her Mind the Squirrel that turns and whirls it round, and her Imagination differs from others, as your Groteſque Figures do from Natural; from Groteſque, in that theſe have ſome
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:135151:81"/> deſign in them, but her Imagination has none; ſhe never looking toward the end, but only the beginning of things; or if ſhe does, forgets or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approves it ſtrait: For ſhe will call in haſte for one, and have nothing to ſay to him when he is come; and long, nay dye, for ſome Toy or Trifle, which having once, ſhe grows weary of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and throws away. In fine, who are of one mind to day, and another tomorrow, are conſtant, to her; and <hi>Saturn</hi>'s Revolution, compar'd to the Moons: For you know not where to have her a moment, and whoſoever would hit her Thoughts, muſt Shoot flying; and fly themſelves, whoſoever would follow her.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="character">
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:135151:81"/>
                  <head>XI. <hi>The Quacks Directory.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HAving obſerved the Prodigious ſucceſs of Modern <hi>Quackery,</hi> and that the Practice of it is lately become a Laſt ſhift, more common and thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving too, then ſelling of <hi>Ale,</hi> or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up a <hi>Coffee-Houſe.</hi> And finding ſtill abundance of indigent Idle People, that could never make their outward Handicrafts fadge to purpoſe, who would be glad to exchange 'em for ſo genteel and advantagious an Imploy, had they but the ſecret Knack, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by other Bankrupts with ſmall pains and Ieſs parts, have in an inſtant rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves from Beggary, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Eſtates. Out of our great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to ſuch hearty well-willers to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ſecure and gainful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ience; we have thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t to unfold the whole <hi>Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> as 'tis this day practiſed with ſo much profit and applauſe: Draw near then with attention, all you decayed <hi>Ragamuffins</hi> of the Town; you by
<pb facs="tcp:135151:82"/> whoſe Dulneſs, no Mechanick Myſtery but ſcorns to be Maſter'd, who neither Sea nor Gibbet will accept; we'll put you in a way of feeding your ſelves and the Worms too: Honeſt no doubt, becauſe common and ſafe; for why, your miſcariages ſhall never be heard for the Dinn of Knells you occaſion — But to deliver our Documents in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> To paſs for currant, you have no more to do but to call your ſelves Doctors; <hi>Pliny</hi> hath affirm'd it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: And though I neither expect nor deſire you ſhou'd underſtand <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> yet becauſe a ſcrap may do you a kindneſs, one time or other to Swag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with, I'll give it you in his own Language: <hi>Hac ſola Arte, evenit quod cuilibet Se Medicum dicenti facile cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur, Cum ſit periculum in nullo Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacio Majus.</hi> In this Art alone it comes to paſs, that any one but profeſſing himſelf a Phyſician, is preſently belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; though in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the belief of a lye be more dangerous. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſht</hi> this for the benefit of thoſe that do not underſtand <hi>Latin;</hi> and I have no quarrel at all againſt thoſe that do.</p>
                  <p>However, in the ſecond place, to
<pb facs="tcp:135151:82"/> ſupport this Title, there are ſeveral things very convenient; of which ſome are External <hi>Accourtrements,</hi> others Internal <hi>Qualifications.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your outward Requiſites, are a decent <hi>Black Suit,</hi> and (if your credit will ſtretch ſo far in <hi>Long-Lane</hi>) a <hi>Pluſh-Jacket;</hi> not a Pin the worſe, though Thread-bare as a Taylors Cloak; it ſhows the more Reverend Antiquity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Like <hi>Mercury,</hi> you muſt always carry a <hi>Caduceus</hi> or <hi>Conjuring-Japan</hi> in your Hand, capt with a <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet-Box;</hi> with which you muſt walk with Spaniſh Gravity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation upon an Arbitrament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Life and Death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> A convenient Lodging, not forgetting a Hatch at the Door: A Chamber hung either with <hi>Dutch</hi> Pictures, or Looking Glaſſes, belitter'd with Urinals or empty Gallipots, and Vials fill'd with Tap-dropings or Fair water, colour'd with Saunders; any Sexton will furniſh your Window with a Skull, in hope of your Cuſtom; over which hang up the Skeleton of a Monkey, to proclaim your Skill in Anatomy.</p>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:135151:83"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> your Table be never without ſome old muſty <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick</hi> Author, and the 4th Book of <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi>'s <hi>Occult Philoſophy,</hi> wide open, to amuſe ſpectators; with half a dozen of <hi>Gilt Shillings,</hi> as ſo many <hi>Guinneys</hi> received that morning for <hi>Fees.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Fail not to oblige Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Ale-houſes, to recommend you to Inquirers; and hold Correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence with all the Nurſes and Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives near you, to applaud your Skill, at Goſſipings.</p>
                  <p>Now to your neceſſary, Quallificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in general two, <hi>viz. Loquacity</hi> or <hi>Talk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tiveneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for the firſt, 'Tis a mighty Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-off amongſt the Vulgar: Be ſure therefore you learn to pronounce <hi>Oppilation</hi> and <hi>Obſtruction</hi> of the Spleen, and <hi>Schirrhous</hi> of the Liver, with a full Mouth: at leaſt ſpeak hard Words, though never ſo wretchedly <hi>miſapply'd,</hi> and obſcure common ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary things in <hi>Terms of Art,</hi> (for all the uſe you are to make of ſuch <hi>Terms,</hi> is the ſame Juglers do of <hi>Hictius Doctius</hi> and <hi>Presto,</hi> to amuſe Peoples
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:135151:83"/> Brains while you pick their Pockets.) If you can but but get ſo far as to call the Fit of an Ague, a <hi>Paroxyſme,</hi> Fits of the Mother, <hi>Hiſterical Paſſions:</hi> Thunder out <hi>Sympathetical</hi> and <hi>Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical</hi> Cures; prate of the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>chaniſme</hi> of Nature, though you know no more on't than a Plowman does of Clock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work. Tell'em of appeaſing the <hi>irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated Archeical Microcoſmical Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,</hi> increaſing the <hi>Radical Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,</hi> and relieving all the Powers, <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, Natural,</hi> and <hi>Animal:</hi> The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring Patient ſhall certainly cry you up for a great Scholard; provided always your nonſenſe be fluent, and mixt with a diſparagement of the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Graduated Doctors, Book-learn'd Phyſicians;</hi> againſt whom you muſt ever be ſure to bring in your high and mighty word <hi>EXPERIENCE.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſince every man is not endued with the Gift of <hi>Tatling,</hi> and 'tis fit you ſhould learn, like a <hi>Dutchman,</hi> to ſail with every Wind: If nigardly Nature, or more penurious Education, have not afforded you a Tongue well hung; make a Virtue of neceſſity, look <hi>Grave</hi> and <hi>Big,</hi> decline all Diſcourſe; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if <hi>Ingenious Men</hi> be by: Tell them
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:135151:84"/> 
                     <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> are not to be frighted away with Words, that you do not come to <hi>Talk</hi> but to <hi>Cure, &amp;c.</hi> This will at once conceal your Ignorance from the Judicious, and increaſe your eſteem for a notable reſerv'd <hi>Paty</hi> Fellow, with others. If any ask the cauſe of their Diſtempers, or reaſon of your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, ſatisfie them both, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing a Liſt of your <hi>mighty Cures;</hi> wherein if one half be <hi>falſe,</hi> and the other <hi>hired,</hi> there is no great danger: For he muſt be a ſtrange inquiſitive Infidel, that will not rather believe them, than give himſelf the trouble of diſproving 'em. Which brings me to the ſecond property,</p>
                  <p>A convenient <hi>Audacity;</hi> There is nothing more neceſſary, nothing more advantagious. Make People believe no Picht ſield e'er <hi>ſlew</hi> or <hi>wounded</hi> half ſo many as you have <hi>recover'd;</hi> That you have made <hi>Death</hi> retreat, where, Nature was more fiercely beleaguer'd than ever <hi>Stetin</hi> was, and diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him of more <hi>Bits</hi> than <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Wars</hi> have furniſh'd him with theſe Forty Years: That you have even <hi>Beckon'd</hi> Souls back again, that have been ſome Leagues onwards their
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:135151:84"/> Journey from their Bodies: Boaſt the wonders that you have done at <hi>Leyden</hi> and <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> the <hi>Lazzaretto</hi> at <hi>Venice,</hi> and the <hi>Maiſons de Dieu</hi> at <hi>Paris:</hi> That your Cloſets are <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality Offices,</hi> and that you can let <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Lives</hi> of a larger Date than a <hi>Suit in Chancery:</hi> Pretend the Cure of all Diſeaſes, eſpecially ſuch as are Incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and to know which are moſt in <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> conſult the <hi>Bills of Mortality;</hi> and next Week vary your Bill accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
                  <p>In particular, Since the whole Art of Phyſick conſiſts in the Diagnoſticks, Prognoſticks, and Therapenticks; For the firſt two you muſt either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be <hi>Waterologers,</hi> or (which is more abſtruſe and modiſh) <hi>Aſs-ſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; Piſs-prophets,</hi> or <hi>Starr-wizards;</hi> either way will do well enough, and to ſpeak truth, are much of a <hi>certainty:</hi> In both there is neceſſary a <hi>Previous pumping,</hi> by apt and wary Queſtions; and their Anſwers handſomely turned into other words, will extreamly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the <hi>Patient</hi> or <hi>Querent.</hi> If you practice by the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinal,</hi> though 'tis as like to diſcover the colour of a Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Cloaths, as his Infirmities; yet
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:135151:85"/> a thouſand to one but with diſcreet handling, you may <hi>ſhake</hi> it into the <hi>Scurvey,</hi> the <hi>Pox,</hi> or the <hi>Conſumption:</hi> Nay you may venture to tell what Trade your Patient is of, by his Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-days Water, and if you ſee but his Sundays Water, what Religion he is of: But if you proceed by the <hi>Scheme,</hi> there is nothing ſo probable as to ſay, He is <hi>Bewitch'd,</hi> under an <hi>Ill-Tongue;</hi> That he is <hi>Planet ſtrucken,</hi> and the Lord of the <hi>Seventh</hi> ſhews you to be the only Doctor in the World that can help him; only here beware that you never pronounce a Common-Councel-Man with <hi>Child,</hi> or a Conſtable Sick of the <hi>Mother;</hi> and in other caſes, if your Judgment chance not to hit the Nail on the Head, 'tis but having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to neceſſary Prudence, called by the Superſtitious, the Art of <hi>Lying.</hi> As to tell 'em their Stomach is fallen out of the place, but you doubt not but to fetch it up again: That they have Straws in their <hi>Lungs</hi> as big as Beams, and their <hi>Livers</hi> waſted with Venery and Drinking. Then as for <hi>Therapenticks,</hi> if your Medicines be <hi>Galenical,</hi> though never ſo <hi>common</hi> diſguiſe them with ſtrange Names
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:135151:85"/> call <hi>Sena, a Specifick; Methridate,</hi> an <hi>Elixir; ExtractumRudii,</hi> an <hi>Arcanum,</hi> and add a <hi>Noſtrum</hi> to <hi>Album Graecum;</hi> But if you would rather betake your ſelf to <hi>Chymical Devices,</hi> and want Nonſenſe to cant their virtues; there are Pamphlets enough abroad to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you. The Tincture of the <hi>Suns Beard;</hi> the Powder of the <hi>Moons Horns;</hi> or a Quinteſſence extracted from the Souls of the <hi>Heathen Gods;</hi> will go off rarely for an Univerſal Medicine; and bubble the ſimple out of their <hi>Money</hi> firſt, and their <hi>Lives</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards.</p>
                  <p>But to deal Ingeniouſly, I will teach you a far more ready and curious way, both of finding out and curing all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, than has yet been diſcovered; which is thus: Take two large Sheets of Paper, on one write down (or get the Book-learn'd Scribe that writes your Bills to do it for you) the names of all ordinary <hi>Diſtempers;</hi> on the other all celeberated Medicines, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Catharticks, Diureticks, Diapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, Emeticks.</hi> Then when any Patient comes or ſends, and you have heard the ſtory, <hi>Retire a while,</hi> telling them a true Phyſician muſt firſt <hi>ſtudy</hi>
                     <pb n="164" facs="tcp:135151:86"/> and then <hi>Preſcribe:</hi> In the mean time, by your ſelf, on the Roll of Infirmities, fling a <hi>Dye,</hi> and as many as the chance is, ſo many Diſeaſes, you may aſſure them the Party has; principally that whereon the <hi>Dye</hi> falls; Then do the ſame on the Paper of <hi>Remedies,</hi> and Preſcribe or Adminiſter that which the <hi>Dye</hi> lights on, to be taken ſo many times as there are ſpots on the chance. And if the ſick be pain'd in the <hi>Head,</hi> you may eaſily Diſcourſe them into a perſwaſion that the Diſeaſe (or at leaſt the <hi>Cauſe</hi>) is in their <hi>Hand</hi> or <hi>Toe:</hi> By which ſafe and ingenious courſe, you ſhall honeſtly refer it to <hi>Fortune,</hi> to diſcover both the Diſeaſe and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine; whereas others through a conceited Knowledg, or unhappy Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, render themſelves more than Acceſſary to the Death of Many.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="character">
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:135151:86"/>
                  <head>XII. <hi>Of a Young Enamouriſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HE's one who as ſoon as he has quitted his School-boys <hi>Toys,</hi> next <hi>Toy</hi> he gets is a Miſtreſs, when 'twould make you forſwear <hi>Love</hi> to ſee how ridiculous he makes it; and to hear him talk of Gods and Goddeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, you would take him for ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan never converted to Chriſtanity. There is nothing ſo cold as to hear him talk of Flames, nor ſo dull as his diſcourſe of <hi>Cupids</hi> darts; and to hear him ſigh like a dry Pump, or broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winded Bellows, you would ne're wonder at <hi>Lapland Witches</hi> affording winds ſo cheap. Of all Servants he is the neceſſarieſt and eaſieſt to content and feed, for he is his Miſtreſſes <hi>Squire, Diſpencer, Laque,</hi> or <hi>Meſſenger;</hi> but above all, her <hi>Fool,</hi> to which he is bound by the Proverb; <hi>'Tis impoſſible to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ove and be wiſe:</hi> Mean time you may
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:135151:87"/> feed him cheaper then a <hi>Camelion,</hi> for a good look ſerves him a week at leaſt, and he is prouder of holding his Miſtreſſes Busk or Fan, then a School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy with a Scepter in his hand, play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Emperours part i'th' School; to keep him to which, his Miſtreſs lets him know that 'tis with Love as 'tis with War, which once declared, you are to expect nothing but Hoſtility; and knows her ſelf, that 'tis with Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers as it is with Anglers, who feed the Fiſh e're they are caught; but caught once, feed on them: whence ſhe bites not greedily at the bait, but craftily tolls him on with hopes, and like a Rope-maker goes backwards ſtill, the better to advance her work, and draw him on; mean while he follows her ſo long, till either he wax weary and ceaſes his purſuit, or catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es her tripping, and then falls down on her, when faſtning her in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage Nooze, he carries her away, and either turns kind <hi>Cuckold,</hi> and keeps open houſe for all; or jealous <hi>Coxcomb,</hi> and ſhuts his door againſt every One.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="character">
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:135151:87"/>
                  <head>XIII <hi>Of an Honeſt Drunken Cur.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HE's a Pickl'd Youth to be ſure, for he always lyes ſteep'd in his own Liquor; of which, like a Whale, he carries ſo much about him, that when-ever he diſgorges, he may ſwim away in his own Flood. Clap but a good Sucker into his Belly, and he makes an excellent Pariſh Pump: And if you add but a Pipe to his Muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle, he may paſs for a Water-Engine, and do good ſervice in time of Fire. You need not fear drawing him dry, ſo long as all the Alehouſes and Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns in Town, like little Rivulets, ſupply the decreaſe: He contains a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout as much as thoſe in Churches; but is ſo uncouth a Trough, he's twice as hard to be Gaug'd: Yet by frequent experience he can gueſs his Meaſure to a Pint, eſpecially if you except Leak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. His Veins are ſo throng'd, and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:135151:88"/> his Blood ſo tainted with Scurvey, Gout and Dropſy, (and a ſmatch of the <hi>French-man</hi> to boot, which he got when he was Drunk, and does not know who to lay it to) That he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Intruſion of any other Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: wherefore he Stalks in as much State through a Peſtilence, as a well Arm'd Souldier through a ſhower of Bullets; for his forementioned Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes have taken ſuch large Poſſeſſion of his Body, that there's no room left for Infection.</p>
                  <p>He has drunk himſelf into a Jelly, and is ſo moiſt, that if you ſqueeſe him, he drops like an Orange.</p>
                  <p>His Body is a perfect Still, which he fuels with Brandy inſtead of Char-coal; being throughly, heated, you may diſcern the ſweaty Diſtilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on tricle from his face, as from the Lid of a Limbeck; and if any chance to drop on his Noſe, you may hear it hiz as if it fell upon heated Bricks. In fine though he always lives Joakingly and Merry, he hates nothing more than a dry Jeſt.</p>
                  <p>Thus having acquainted you with his Conſtitution, I ſhall only conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him in his Converſation, and
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:135151:88"/> Friendſhip, and ſo leave him to ſleep out his nap.</p>
                  <p>And firſt for his Converſation; To take him in the Morning (for who can find him all the Day after?) he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents his Prayers with a Pipe of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, and Smoaks at ſuch a Rate, as if he prefer'd Sacrifice to Devotion. A Tinder-box is as neceſſary to him, as a green Bagg to an Atturney's Clark, with which he ſeems as raviſh'd as <hi>Alexander</hi> with the Odiſſes, for he cannot ſleep unleſs it lye under his Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. In that little night he makes, he cannot ſo properly be ſaid to ſleep, as to Chew the Cudd on his Quotidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Debauchery; for he often diſturbs the repoſe of a Family, with Muttering a Repetition of his Oaths and Healths. When he awakes, he ſtares about with ſuch wild Curioſity, as one wou'd fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy <hi>Adam</hi> did immediately after his Creation; for he generally makes himſelf ſo Drunk over Night, drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his paſt Actions in Liquor and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion, that he ſcarcely knows the the Morning from the Reſnrrection, and is hardly perſwaded that ever he liv'd before.</p>
                  <p>But after he is convinc'd of the
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:135151:89"/> affirmative, ſpends about a quarter of of an Hour in examining the Bed-poſts and Windows, before he diſcovers whether he be in his own Lodging: And afterwards remains as doubtfull how he got thither.</p>
                  <p>Then Bed-ſtaves and Slip-ſhoos go towrack, for clattering on the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead, like Boys at the Bear-Garden, he calls up the People as Countrey We nches do Swine, by knocking; and after a Petition for a Cup of Settle-Brain, begs them to reſolve his Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; whereupon they tell him the truth, which indeed is, that either he came the old Porterly way, Cruch'd with a brace of Watch-men; or elſe the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern and more Genteel way, <hi>viz.</hi> On Pick-pack, inſtead of a Sedan.</p>
                  <p>Now although my <hi>Honeſt Drunken Curr</hi> be guilty of many Vices, which like Younger Brothers hang on this great one, which has got poſſeſſion; Yet (<hi>Give the Devil his due</hi>) I think the World has Sully'd his Reputation with divers Scandals of which he is no ways Guilty: Wherefore becauſe only intend his Converſion, not his Conſumption; Like an honeſt Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ince I write his Life) I ought not
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:135151:89"/> to ſee him wrong'd, but rather to reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue him from thoſe Callumnies thrown on him, by perſons in ſome reſpects worſe then himſelf.</p>
                  <p>The firſt imputation therefore that they impoſe on him, is that he is proud: <hi>And why for ſooth?</hi> but becauſe when he has a <hi>Drop in his Eye;</hi> he brags as if he were a better man then his Neighbours. A ſtout reaſon indeed! as if a man might not do as much, that were either Light-headed, or in a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; Nay, Paſſion alone makes the wiſeſt of us <hi>Bedlams.</hi> But let us do as we would be done by, and take him when he is himſelf, (that is, in a Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) and then I am ſure he is as free from Pride, as a Quaker from good Manners or Ribonds: for would Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom admit, I am confident he would rather go to the Ale-houſe Naked, than undergo the hard Pennance of Sobriety while he dreſſes himſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> They call him <hi>an Idle fellow:</hi> a good fellow all the Word knows he is, but as for idleneſs, let me dye if I know any one more free from it then he; What would they have of him trow? he riſes early, ſits up late; and I dare Swear he grudges himſelf
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:135151:90"/> his very Sleep, becauſe it keeps him from his Buſineſs: When he is at it, no Man more expeditious then he; for as if his Minutes, like his Eſtate, ran away too faſt, you ſhall frequently ſee him with an Ale Glaſs in one hand, and a Looking-Glaſs in the other, which betokens both ſpeed and fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
                  <p>The third and moſt fallacious Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fation is, that they ſay, <hi>He's Prodigal, and Piſſes his Eſtate againſt the Wall.</hi> But I am confident he Enriches or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes the Walls no more than others; onely this I know he does, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Uſurers uſe to hide their Riches in Earthen Pots, he puts his Eſtate in a Pewter one, (which one would think were the ſafer Cabinet) ſo that it is not the <hi>Honeſt Drunken Curr,</hi> but the Impudent Rogues, <hi>Drawers</hi> and <hi>Tap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> that imbezle and make it away. Much more might be ſaid of him both in his Vindication, and in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation alſo: For he is one of the quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Subjects his Majeſty has, and moſt ſubmiſſive to Monarchical Government. He would not be without a King, if it were for no other Reaſon than meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Drinking his Health. He hates
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:135151:90"/> Coffee, but dare not enter on a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thought, or if hee doe, it is ſuch Melancholy that it ſends him to be drunke againe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="character">
                  <head>XIV. <hi>A Baker.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NO man verifies the Proverbe more, that it is an Almeſ-deed to puniſh him: for his penalty is a Dole, and do's the Beggers as much good as their Dinner. Hee abhors therefore workes of Charitie, and thinkes his Bread caſt away when it is given to the poore. He loves not Iuſtice neither, for the <hi>weigh-ſcales ſake,</hi> and hates the Clarke of the Market as his Executioner: yet hee finds mercy in his offences, and his Basket onely is ſent to Priſon. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a Pillory is his deadly enemy, and hee never heares well after.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:135151:91"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135151:91"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of BOOKS, newly Printed for <hi>John Harris,</hi> at the <hi>Harrow,</hi> againſt the <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>[1] <hi>THe Conviction of Worldly Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> Or, The Wandring Prodigal, and his Return: In Two Parts.
<list>
                     <item>PART I. Containing his debate with himſelf about his ſetting forward in ſearch of the Palace of <hi>Worldly Felicity;</hi> His hearkening to the Advice of <hi>Folly,</hi> and ſubmitting himſelf to her Conduct; the manner of her furniſhing him out; of the Progreſs he made, and the various Adventures he met with by the way: As alſo the Entertainment he found at his Arrival, and his Rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
<pb facs="tcp:135151:92"/> Living there; With his Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Vices Reigning therein.</item>
                     <item>PART II. Giving a full Account of his Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Eſcape from the Palace of <hi>Worldly Felicity:</hi> Of the glorious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect he had of the <hi>Coeleſtial City;</hi> And of the Progreſs he made towards it, under the Conduct of <hi>Divine Grace:</hi> With the manner of his Proceeding, and the ſeveral Occurrences he met with by the way: His Arrival at the Palace of <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>True Felicity,</hi> and his Joyful Reception there: His Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Deſcription thereof, and of the Divine and Moral Vertues which he found therein. Both Pleaſant and Profitable. Deliver'd under the Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of <hi>A Wandring Youth.</hi> Illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Proper Cutts.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Price Bound One Shilling.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>[2] Come and Welcom to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Or a plain and profitable <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> on <hi>John</hi> 6. Verſe 37. Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cauſe, Truth and Manner of the Coming of a <hi>Sinner</hi> to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> with his Happy Reception, and Bleſſed Entertainment, by <hi>John Bunnyan,</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Pilgrims Progreſs. Price Bound One Shilling.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:135151:92"/>
               <item>[3] <hi>A Diſcourſe</hi> upon the <hi>Phariſee</hi> and the <hi>Publican.</hi> Wherein ſeveral great and weighty things are handled: As the nature of Prayer, and of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Law; with how far it obliges Chriſtians, and wherein it conſiſts: Wherein is alſo ſhewed the equally deplorable condition of the <hi>Phariſee,</hi> or Hypocrital and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous <hi>Man,</hi> and of the <hi>Publican</hi> or Sinner that lives in Sin, and in violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Divine Laws: Together, wirh the Way and Method of God's Free Grace in Pardoning Penitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; proving that he juſtifies them by imputing Chriſts Righteouſneſs to them. Price Bound One Shilling.</item>
               <item>[4] <hi>A Diſcourſe of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, 1. In General:</hi> That there is a Providence Exerciſed by God in the World. 2. <hi>In Particular:</hi> How all Gods Providences in the World, are in order to the good of his People. By the late Learned Divine <hi>Stephen Charnock, E. D.</hi> ſometimes Fellow of <hi>New Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxon.</hi> Price Bound Three Shillings.</item>
               <item>[5] <hi>The Saints Comfort,</hi> in all, but more eſpecially in <hi>Evil times.</hi> Drawn
<pb facs="tcp:135151:93"/> from Twelve ſeveral Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; which are briefly explained in this ſmall Piece, By <hi>T. G.</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel. Price Bound One Shilling.</item>
               <item>[6] <hi>A Preſent for Ladies.</hi> The Nymphs of <hi>Diana;</hi> or the Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Women kind, deſcrib'd as well in their External Beauty, as Internal Virtue; being an Advocate for the <hi>Fair Sex;</hi> compriz'd in an Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Hiſtory of it. Repreſented not only in Lively and Pathetical Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes grounded upon Reaſon, but in ſundry rare Examples of <hi>Virtuous Love, Piety, Prudence, Modeſty, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, Patience, Humility, Temperance, Conduct, Conſtancy,</hi> and <hi>Firmneſs of Mind;</hi> With what elſe in the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is neceſſary to the Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the moſt <hi>Celebrated Beauties.</hi> With other Examples of Women skill'd in the moſt curious <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences.</hi> To which are Added, The Examples of <hi>Warlike</hi> Women, their <hi>Noble Exploits</hi> and <hi>Victories:</hi> With the <hi>Prophecies</hi> and <hi>Predictions</hi> of the <hi>Sybils,</hi> in Relation to our <hi>Saviour Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> And as an <hi>Apendix,</hi> the Character of a <hi>Virtuous</hi> Woman in all her <hi>Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="tcp:135151:93"/> viz.</hi> Of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> of a <hi>Wife,</hi> and of a <hi>Widow;</hi> Wherein is ſhew'd, the happineſs that accrues to Man in the poſſeſſion of ſo great a Bleſſing, as a <hi>Virtuous</hi> Woman; with the Reaſons why Man's happineſs is not compleat on Earth, without the Charming Creature <hi>Woman.</hi> The whole Work Enrich'd and Intermix'd with Curious <hi>Poetry,</hi> and Delicate <hi>Fancie,</hi> ſuitable to ſo <hi>Charming a Sudject.</hi> Price Bound One Shilling.</item>
               <item>[7] <hi>The True Fortune-Teller:</hi> Or, <hi>Guide to Knowledge.</hi> Diſcovering the whole Art of <hi>Chyromancy, Phyſiognomy, Metopoſcopy</hi> and <hi>Aſtrology.</hi> Contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1. A deſcription of the Planets, their power and influence over the Bodies of Men, Women, and Children. 2. Of the ſeveral Lines, Mounts, Marks, Angles, and ſacred Characters in the Hand and Wriſt; and by what Planets they are governed as to good or bad Fortune. 3. Of Phyſiognomy. 4. Obſervations on the Eyes, Eyebrows, Noſe, Chin, Neck, Hair, Beard and Face. 5. Metopoſcopy, or the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the Lines in the Face. 6. Of Moles, and their ſignifications. 7. Of Dreams, and their interpretations.
<pb facs="tcp:135151:94"/> 8. Of Nativities, and their calculation. 9. Of the Rod, by which hidden Treaſure is found. 10. Of Marriage, and at what time any Perſon ſhall be Married. 11. Rules to know the danger of Death. 12. Of good and bad Days. 13. The manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving doubtful Queſtions, as to Friends, Marriages, places of Abode, Health, Proſperity or Adverſity, Love or Buſineſs. 14. Of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> his Wheel of Fortune. Of the good and bad Days in each Month relating to Health. To which are Added, <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotles</hi> Obſervations on the Heavens, their Motion. Of Fiery Meteors, Thunder, Lightning, Eclipſes, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets, Earth-quakes and Whirl-winds. Illuſtrated with ſeveral Proper Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures. <hi>The ſecond Edition.</hi> Price Bound One Shilling.</item>
               <item>[8] A Pleaſant and Compendious <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> of the firſt <hi>Inventers</hi> and <hi>Inſtituters,</hi> of the moſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Arts, Myſteries, Laws, Cuſtoms,</hi> and <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> in the whole World, (<hi>viz</hi>) 1. Of Arithmetick or Numbers. 2. Aſtrology. 3. Alchimy. 4. Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aters and Theaters. 5. Books, by whom firſt made, and where Publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed. 6. Bells. 7. Baths. 8. Barbers. 9 Coin. 10. The Carpenters Art. 11. Common Wealths. 12. Councils. 13. Charms. 14. Crowns or Garlands. 15. Democracy. 16. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination, Natural and Artificial. 17. Dreams, the firſt Expound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of them. 18 Divorcement. 19. Dials. 20. Fire, the admirable way of firſt finding it out. 21. Funerals, the various manners, and Rites
<pb facs="tcp:135151:94"/> of them amongſt ſeveral Nations. 22. Grace, or the Hallowing of the Table and Meat. 23. God-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and God-Mothers. 24. Good and Bad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, their Offices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 25. Grammar. 26. Guns. 27. Geometry. 28. Games, the ſeveral ſorts of them. 29. Herbs, the wonderful uſe of them, and effects wrought by them, with the firſt Inventer of ſuch Medicines that were made with them. 30. The Harp. 31. Husbandry, the firſt Inventers of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of it, (<hi>viz.</hi>) of the Plow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 32. Wine, and Wine-Taverns, where, and by whom firſt ſet up. 33. Ale, the making of it. 34. Oil, Cheeſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 35. Hiſtories. 36. Hunting, and Fiſhing. 37. Warrens, and Parks. 38. the Smith's Forge. 39. Of the Law, the three kinds of it, (<hi>viz.</hi>) Natural, National and Civil. 40. Lots. 41. Looking Glaſſes, the ſtrange way of finding out Glaſs. 42. Lamps, Laws of Mourning, Letting of Blood, of whom firſt learn'd. 43. Lead. 44. Letters. 45. Marriage, the ſtrange and different cuſtoms of ſeveral Nations ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in it. 46. Mahomets Sect, the firſt Riſe, Growth and Encreaſe of it. 47. Muſick. 48. Magick. 49. Monks and Fryers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 50. Martyrs, giving the Hiſtory of the Ten great Perſecutions, and of the Martyrdom of the Apoſtles. 51. Of the Four Monarchys of the World, their Riſe, Growth, and Peroid. 52. Meaſures and Weights. 53. Men Deified. 54. Men firſt call'd Chriſtians, when, and where. 55. Necromancy. 56. Pyromancy. 57. Hieromancy. 58. Hydromancy. 59. Geomancy. 60. Chyromancy, their Deſcriptions and Authors of them. 61. Naval Fights. 62. Nets. 63. Notaries. 64. Nuns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 65. Orders of Chivalry or Knighthood, the ſeveral ſorts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 66. Obiliſci, or Pyramids. 67. Original of the Heathen Gods. 68. The Opinions of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, concerning the Birth of Man. 69. Painting. 70. Paper. 71. Parchment. 72. Printing. 73. Poetry. 74. Pardons. 75. Philoſophy. 76. Prayer. 77. Preaching, who Preach'd the firſt Sermon. 78. Rhetorick. 79. Reliques. 80. Satyr, a Poem againſt Vice. 81. Ships, of the ſeveral ſorts of them, and who made the firſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 82. silk, who firſt Spin'd and Weav'd it. 83. Swearing, the firſt ordainer of it. 84. Temples or Churches. 85. Tragedies and Comedies. 86. Writing. 87. The Winds, the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:135151:95"/> obſerver of them. 88. Of the ſeven Wonders of the World. To which are Added, ſeveral curious Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, peculiarly attributed to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. The whole Work Alphabetically Digeſted, and very helpful to the Readers of Hiſtory. Price Bound One Shilling.</item>
               <item>[9] <hi>A Directory for Midwives:</hi> Or, <hi>a Guide for Women</hi> in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, Bearing, and Suckling their Children. The firſt part containes, 1. The Anatomy of the veſſels of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. 2. The formation of the Child in the Womb. 3. What hinders con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and its Remedies. 4. What furthers Conception. 5. A Guide for Women in Conception. 6. Of Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in Women. 7. A Guide for Women in their Labour. 8. A Guide for Women in Lying-in. 9. Of Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Children. By <hi>Nicholas Culpepper.</hi> Price Bound 3 S.</item>
               <item>[10] <hi>Twelve Ingenious Characters:</hi> Or, <hi>Pleaſant Deſcriptions,</hi> of the Properties of ſundry <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Things, viz.</hi> An Importunate-Dun, a Serjeant or Baylif, a Paun-Broker, a Priſon, a Tavern, a Scold, a Bad-Husband, a Town-Fop, a Bawd, a fair and happy Milk-Maid, the <hi>Quacks</hi> Directory, a Young Enamoriſt. <hi>Price Sticht</hi> 3 d.</item>
            </list>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:135151:95"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
